<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The churches resurrection, or, The creating of the new heavens written by an unworthy gospel-minister, John Bryan.</title>
            <author>Brayne, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 195 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29276</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4321</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23804</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07911444</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07911444</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40358</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29276)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40358)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1198:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The churches resurrection, or, The creating of the new heavens written by an unworthy gospel-minister, John Bryan.</title>
                  <author>Brayne, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for George Whittington,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church polity.</term>
               <term>Church history.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40358:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40358:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHURCHES RESURRECTION: <hi>OR,</hi> The CREATING of the New Heavens.</p>
            <p>Written by an unworthy Goſpel-Miniſter, <hi>JOHN BRAYN.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rev. 21.2.</hi>
                  </bibl> And I John ſaw the holy City, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Acts 13.41,</hi>
                  </bibl> Behold, ye deſpiſers, and wonder, and periſh: for I work a work in your days, a work which you ſhall in no wiſe believe, though a man declare it unto you.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>George Whittington,</hi> at the Blew-Anchor in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> near the Royal-Exchange. 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40358:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40358:2"/>
            <head>To the Honorable, The General Councel OF THE ARMY.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N that <hi>I</hi> am aſſured you and your despiſed Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, are they by whom the Church is to be uſhered out of her long hid eſtate into the world again; I preſume to preſent you with this inſuing Tract, as belonging to you, which may ſomething ſerve to help-direct your Councels in Church-affairs, in the ſound foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation whereof you will finde to conſiſt the ſtrength of your undertakings, Councels and comforts to depend, and iſſues to ſucceed, it being the work onely of God, to give man to his labor an expected end. Now the Lord ſo direct you in your great undertakings, to do the work of the Lord, that he may have glory, and you mercy in the day of Chriſt, is the deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant in the Goſpel, JO: BRAYN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:40358:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>I Think good to acquaint thee, that God may have the greater glory, That the Form of Government I drew wholly from the Word, before I ſaw the leaſt footſtep of it in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Practice, mentioned by the Fathers; which when I came to ſee them to be as ſo many Witneſſes to the Truth, I could not for the Truths ſake but make it publique for thy profit. It is not as large as intended, but Epitomized onely, my allowance for my Miniſtery being detained from me; nor did I therefore tranſlate but few of the Authorities cited; ſome are, for the uſe of the unlearned. I deſire you to paſs by the errors committed in Printing it, becauſe having other occaſions, I could not attend the Preſs, and it ſhall be your honor, and be eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Servant in the Gospel,</hi> JO: BRAYN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:40358:3"/>
            <p>IN theſe times it hath been the way of men to cry down the ſound and ſaving Truths of God and the Goſpel, by branding them with terms of <hi>Novelty,</hi> and <hi>New found Notions,</hi> proudly and ſcornfully calling them ridiculous things, in branding the men that God reveals them to with odious names, hindring many from ſo much as trying the Truth; then which, Satan hath not had a greater Engine againſt the way of God in theſe laſt times, which the tryal of the firſt and pureſt of Antiquity will reveal unto us, and ſhew us how; and I ſhall endeavor, as my weak ability, ſmall reading, and other great imployments will give me leave, in theſe few ſheets of Paper fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing to manifeſt. And firſt,</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the Government of the Church in the Primitive times, was not looked on as in theſe latter times it hath been (even to be a thing to be made conformal to every eſtate in which the Goſpel is preached prudentially) which is clearly to be proved by many witneſſes; but in that the Scripture ſaith, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder two or three witneſſes every thing ſhall be eſtabliſhed,</hi> I ſhall onely prove them by two or three, and no more, as being ſufficient hereunto alone.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who lived about Two hundred years after Chriſt, ſaith, <hi>Nobis vero nihil ex noſtro arbitrio inducere licet, ſed nec eligere quod aliquis ex ſuo arbitrio induxerit, Apoſtolos Domini habemus auctores, qui nec ipſi quicquam ex ſuo arbitrio quod inducerent eligerunt, ſed acceptam à Chriſto diſciplinam fideliter Nationibus aſſignarunt ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> etiamſi Angelus de coelis aliter Evangelizaret, anathema diceretur à nobis.</hi> De Praeſcrip. Heret.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:40358:4"/>
            <p>The ſence this: It is not lawful for us to induce any thing at our pleaſure, nor to chooſe that any one hath induced of his own will; we have the Apoſtles of the Lord, Authors, who themſelves nor choſe nor brought in (to the Church) any thing of their free will, but they faithfully aſſigned to the Nations the diſcipline received from Chriſt: Therefore, though an Angel from heaven ſhould teach otherways, let him be accounted as accurſed of us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ap.</hi> What place is there then for a prudential Government in the Church? How can Miniſters plead for it, or Magiſtrates ſet it up?</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Dioniſius</hi> Ep. to <hi>Demophilus.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Si diſtinctiones ordineſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> confundere Sacratiſſimas Dei Sanctiones jura tranſgredi eſt, omni profectò ratione caret Dei cauſâ pervertere traditum divinitùs ordinem; ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> enim in ſeipſum Dei ſermo diviſus eſt, alioquin quomodo ſtaret ejus regnum?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Clem. Alex. Lib. Strom. 7. p. 841.</head>
               <p>Quomodo ergo in bello non eſt ordo deſerendus quem dedit imperator militi, ita nec eſt deſerendus ordo quem dedit nobis verbum, quem ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepimus principem ac ducem cognitionis &amp; vitae.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I may prove this by others, but</hi> Tertull. <hi>whoſe Authority is que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned by none, ſpeaking to this exceeding pertinently, I propoſe again, as in his Book</hi> Adverſus Marcion.</p>
               <p>Et oportuerit uti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> prius alium Deum exponi, poſtea ejus diſciplinam induci; quia Deus auctoritatem praeſtet diſciplinae, non Deo diſciplina.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This I ſuppoſe proves ſufficiently, That in the Church no Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline ought to be ſet up, but what Chriſt in the Goſpel hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſecond thing to be conſidered, is, The Miniſtery without the Church, erected by Chriſt in the world to fit for the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1. The Books of</hi> Arnobius, Lactantius, Juſtin Martyr, <hi>called</hi> Serm. ad Gentes, <hi>prove it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Clem. Alex. ad Gentes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Venite, venite ô meorum juvenum caetus niſi: enim rurſus efficiamini ut pueri, &amp; regeneremini ut ait Scriptura eum qui vero eſt pater non recipietis, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> unquam in regnum Coelorum intrabitis, quando enim eſt hoſpiti permiſſum ingredi, ſed quando ut puto inſcriptus fuerit &amp; cives effectus, &amp; patrem acceperit; tunc erit in numero filiorum patris, tunc dignus habebitur qui ſit haeres.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:40358:4"/>
               <p>Come ye, come ye, O Congregation of my yong men, for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ye become again as children, and be new born, as the Scripture ſaith, ye cannot receive him who is truly the Father, nor ſhall ye ever enter into the Kingdom of Heaven: When is it permitted the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to enter, but when, as I think, he is inrolled and made a Citizen, and hath received the Father? then he ſhall be in the number of the Fathers children.</p>
               <p>That this was to unconverted Gentiles, is without doubt; and farther ſhews, They were to be inrolled, and receive the Father (that is, I ſuppoſe) they were to profeſs Faith in and Obedience unto God, before he could be a Citizen or a Son, which at firſt muſt be an eſtate of childehood in the Church again (though men by nature) or they could not enter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Clemens in Orat. adhor. ad Gentes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Praecurſor Johannis vox verbum praecurrit, vox adhortatoria prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parans ad ſalutem, vox adhortans, ad haereditatem Coelorum per quam ſterilis &amp; deſerta non eſt infertilis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſhews what the work of this Miniſtery was, even onely to prepare for, and perſwade men of the neceſſity there was to become members of the Church, and to be of the ſociety of the Saints, that the barren and the deſert ſouls may not be unfruitful, he alluding herein to <hi>Johns</hi> preaching in the wilderneſs of <hi>Judea.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Tertull. adverſus Marcion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lex &amp; Prophetae uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad Joannem ex quo regnum Dei annuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quaſi non &amp; nos limitem quendam agnoſcamus Joannem conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum inter vetera &amp; nova ad quem deſineret Judaiſmus, &amp; à quo inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peret Chriſtianiſmus: non tamen, &amp; ab alia virtute facta ſit ſedatio le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis &amp; prophetarum &amp; initiatio Evangelii in quo eſt Dei regnum Chriſtus ipſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. This Miniſtery in <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> was ſet up among the Jews, Gods own ancient people, to prepare them for the Goſpel eſtate, which proves the Miniſtery to be exerciſed among all other people, to prepare them for the Church eſtate, if it had been needleſs among any, it had been among the Jews.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This Miniſtery is clearly confirmed by the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.11. who is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; here Apoſtle and Teacher are the two extremes of the Church, Miniſtery the firſt and laſt, higheſt and loweſt, between which, the Prophet, the Evangeliſt and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40358:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> Paſtor are contained; before all which, the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is placed, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares for the Church Miniſtery, but is not of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Euſebius Lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cum Eccleſiae apud Alexandriam Magiſterii deeſſet officium, cum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> omnes perturbati perſequtorum minis &amp; ferocitatibus anfugiſſent, aliquanti Gentilium conveniebant ad Originem tunc adhuc Grammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum docentem audire de eo verbum de noſtra fide ac Religione Cupien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes; quos ille non tantum ad fidem de perfidia convertebat, ſed etiam perfectae vitae inſtitutionibus informabat.</hi> Hence Mr. <hi>More</hi> in his <hi>Chronol. Tables,</hi> calls <hi>Origen</hi> Catechiſt, as if he had obtained no other degree of Miniſtery.</p>
               <p>It is remarkable he ſaith, he did not onely convert them from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity to the Faith (which was the proper work of the Miniſtery without the Church, and ſo here implyed) but informed them in the Inſtitutions of a better life.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This was more, I ſuppoſe, then any before <hi>Origen</hi> ever did by an ordinary Call.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is true, the Miniſtery were all fled, and ſo none left to do it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Called on of the people to do it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A word or two will not be amiſs, to ſhew the maner of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to Church ſociety, as recorded by the Ancients.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Clem. Alex. Lib. <hi>7,</hi> pag. <hi>834.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Num ergo ſi quis pacta conventa non obſervaverit, &amp; tranſgreſſus fuerit eam quae fit apud nos confeſſionem, propter eum qui non ſtetit ſuae profeſſioni abſtinebimus nos quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> à veritate? ſed ut oportet virum probum minimè eſſe mendacem &amp; nihil infirmare eorum quae eſt polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus, etiamſi aliqui alia pacta conventa tranſiliant, ita nos quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> nullo modo convenit tranſilire regulam eccleſiaſticam, &amp; maximè eam quae fit de rebus maximis profeſſionem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tertul. de Spectaculis: <hi>Cum aquam ingreſſi Chriſtianam fidem in legis ſuae verba profitemur, renunciaſſe nos diabolo &amp; pompae ejus &amp; Angelis ejus ore noſtro conteſtamur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dioniſius cap.</hi> 2. <hi>de Hierar.</hi> ſets it out thus, He that is taken with the love and deſire of ſublime and celeſtial benefits, comes to one of the number of the faithful, and deſires him to bring him to the Prieſt, promiſing he would obſerve all that ſhould be required of him with his whole heart; deſiring him he would alſo take the care of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40358:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> ordering of his remaining life. Now although the believer be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed with a ſacred love of the ſalvation of his ſoul, yet conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the height of the thing, and humane infirmity, forthwith horror and diſtreſs invade him: At length he bountifully promiſeth him to do what is deſired, and taking the man, brings him to the high Prieſt (or Evangeliſt) who with great joy receives the man no otherways then as a loſt ſheep on his ſhoulders; then he (that is, the high Prieſt) gathers all the ſacred Orders, that they may co-operate with him (which is the Paſtor and Teacher, admitting him for a Member) and that they may rejoyce together for the man, and as the holy Church (that is, the ſociety of the Saints) they give thanks to the Divine Clemency, and in the beginning ſingeth ſome Hymn, inſerted in the ſacred Books, together with all the Orders of the Church, <hi>poſt haec deoſculatis Sanctis altaribus:</hi> After this, the Prieſt comes to the man ſtanding by, and demands of him, What moved him to come there; he accuſing himſelf (as he was taught by him that took the charge of him) of ungodlineſs, and ignorance of the true God, and ſighing for that he hath been ſo long deſtitute of the work of the divine life; and praying, That by his moſt ſacred Office and Prayer, he may be permitted to enjoy God and the Divine Myſteries. Now on this it is witneſſed unto him by the Prieſt, that he ought to come to God with his whole heart, and in all things to be perfect and unblame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. Then the Prieſt opening the nature of a divine Converſation and life, it is demanded of him, if he will live ſo, yea or no; which when he hath promiſed, he puts his hand on his head, <hi>Conſignanſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> illum,</hi> he commits him to the Prieſts, they Record the man, and him that undertook for him. Other Ceremonies are by the perverters of Antiquity added after, which I paſs by as ſpurious things, and then the Evangeliſt, Paſtor and Teacher proceed to the Baptizing of him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Clem. Alex. Lib. <hi>7.</hi> Stro. p. <hi>790.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nam ante myſteriorum quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſeu Sacramentorum traditionem ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hiberi oportere quaſdam expiationes iis qui ſunt initiandi myſteriis; utpote quod oporteat impia depoſita opinione ad veram converti tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Herein that this was done to thoſe were to be initiated, at their initiating (by the myſteries) that is, at their Baptiſm; before which they were to promiſe the denyal of themſelves, and the forſaking their old Converſation, and a ſubjecting themſelves to the Goſpel,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40358:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> and promiſe to live the life of Chriſt, in ſociety with the Saints.</p>
               <p>Now in theſe do I ſuppoſe begins the bonds and tyes ſpoken of <hi>Epheſians</hi> 4.16. <hi>Colloſſ.</hi> 3.19. in which, the member is bound to Chriſt, to the Miniſter, the members by Promiſe, by Sacraments, by Profeſſion of Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and Chriſt unto the Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>Application of this is, That ſeeing the collection of Churches was in this maner ſet down in the Goſpel, and practiſed for Two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years after in the Church, ſure the ſame way is ſtill to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, or the conſtitution of our Churches cannot be ſaid to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Chriſt in the Goſpel, or the Churches in the Primitive pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern; but muſt reſemble the eſtate of Churches as they were ſet up under Antichriſt, or that Form which made way for him, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the inthronizing of him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Juſtin. Apol. <hi>2.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Euchariſtae nemo admittitur niſi qui credit veram eſſe noſtram doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, ablutus regenerationis lavacro in remiſſionem peccatorum, &amp; ſic vivens ut Chriſtus docuit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The fourth general is of the Miniſtery, that appertains unto the Church onely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Their number are ſaid to be three onely.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Tertull. de Exhort. Caſtitatis.</head>
               <p>Differentiam inter ordinem &amp; plebem conſtituit eccleſia auctoritas &amp; honor per ordinis confeſſum ſanctificatus à Deo, ubi non eſt eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtici ordinis conſeſſus, &amp; Offers, &amp; Tingis, &amp; Sacerdos es tibi ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, ſed ubi tres, eccleſia eſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The words for the Miniſtery are</hi> obſolete; <hi>but he that is not a ſtranger to his Writings, will not admire at it, eſpecially in his</hi> Apolog.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Dioniſius Eccleſ. Hierar. cap <hi>5.</hi> par. prima.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nunc jam Sacerdotalis perfunctio ſuo eſt loco, exponenda, in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantem at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> illuminantem Conſummantem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ordinem diſtributa,</hi> which he calls <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>Miniſter, Sacerdos, Pontifex.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, ſaith he, the Sacerdotal Calling is to be expounded in its place, and is diſtributed into the Purging Order, which is the Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, the illuminating the Paſtors, and the Perfecting Order, which is the Evangeliſts.</p>
               <p>And after <hi>idem ibid.</hi> he clears it thus, <hi>Rudes hactenus purgat, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> purgatos ratione Sacratioris eruditionis illuminat, ultima quae
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40358:6"/> &amp; priores concludet &amp; complet quod ineruditos Suarum inſtructio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ſcientia perfecit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which plainly proves the Miniſtery then exerciſed in the Church, to be threefold, and diſtinguiſhed by the operations of them, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, illuminating, perfecting, and by the Order they are placed in the Church; as, the firſt Miniſtery, the middle Miniſtery, the laſt Miniſtery.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Ep. Decretal</hi> of <hi>Lucius</hi> it is ſaid, That a Biſhop ſhould have two Prieſts and three Deacons following him, which was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for the conſtituting of a Church according to the Goſpel, and not for pompous pride, as Papiſts underſtand for Popes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Ignatius Ep.</hi> to the Church of <hi>Trallis.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quid vero Preſbyterium niſi collegium Sacrum? conſiliarii &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſores Epiſcopi: quid item Diaconi niſi imitatores Angelicarum virtutem ei miniſtrantes miniſterium purum &amp; immaculatum ut San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus Stephanus beato Jacobo, &amp; Timotheus ac Linus Paulo, &amp; Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cletus at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Clemens Petro? qui igitur inobediens fuerit his Atheus &amp; impius omninò fuerit &amp; Christum improbans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I the ſooner quote this Epiſtle, becauſe not queſtioned, and this matter, becauſe its uſed by <hi>Ignatius</hi> demonſtratively; in which he proves their Presbytery, conſiſting of a Biſhop and two Presbyters, to agree with that of <hi>Paul, Timothy</hi> and <hi>Linus, Peter, Anacletus</hi> and <hi>Clemens,</hi> and ſo to be according to the Apoſtolical inſtitution: This Epiſtle ſpoken of by <hi>Nicephor, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 29. <hi>Hyreneus. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The reaſon why <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſpeaks ſo little of theſe things in his Five Books, <hi>Adverſ. Haereſ.</hi> I ſuppoſe is, becauſe he wrote a Book <hi>De Diſciplina,</hi> mentioned by <hi>Hieron. de vita Iraenei,</hi> which with the true Hiſtory of <hi>Egiſip.</hi> and that Book of <hi>Joſep. Antioch.</hi> called <hi>Speculum perfectae militiae eccleſiae Primitivae,</hi> are all loſt; and the beginning of the firſt <hi>Lib.</hi> of <hi>Strom.</hi> of <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> which was the Key of his Books of <hi>Stromes</hi> doubtleſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Hyraen. Lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>43.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quapropter eis qui in eccleſia ſunt Preſbyteris obaudire oportet his qui ſucceſſionem habent ab Apoſtolis ſicut oſtendimus, qui cum Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copatus ſucceſſione Chariſma veritatis certum, ſecundum placitum patris acceperunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In which he ſhews, That in every Church there ought to be Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, who are to have their ſucceſſion from the Apoſtles.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:40358:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>This may be ſeen in <hi>Origen. Euſeb. Hiſt. Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Videns De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrius Epiſcopus quod ad ipſum praecipuè doctrinae gratiâ &amp; praedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis verbi multitudines plurimae convolarent, &amp; Calezizandi ei, id est, docendi magiſterium in eccleſia tribuit,</hi> which I take to be Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizing.</p>
               <p>Lib. 6. cap: 5. <hi>Nam cum apud Palaeſtinam praecipui &amp; eminentes inter Epiſcopos viri id est, Hieroſolimorum Alexander, &amp; Theotiſtus, Ceſareae, videntes divinum opus verbo Dei ordinaſſent eum Preſbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, ac eum Sacerdotio jam nam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> dignum probarent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sacerdos</hi> is uſually applyed to the Paſtors Miniſtery, which he was thought worthy of, but received it not; which proves this Presbyter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip he now received, was nothing elſe but the Doctors office, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears more clearly in the words following, <hi>Origines apud Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driam Doctor eccleſiae valdè clarus habebatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lib. 6. cap. 17. <hi>Poſt Philetum autem apud Antiochiam Zebenus eccleſiam ſuſcepit, quo in tempore Origines rogatus eſt ab eccleſiis;</hi> (that is, the diſtinct Societies at <hi>Antioch) apud Antiochiam ut illò uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> pro convincendis haereticis qui inibi liberius convaluerant perveniret, quò cum pergeret &amp; iter neceſſariò ageret per Paleſtinam, Preſbyter apud Caeſaream ab illius provinciae Epiſcopis ordinatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. By his firſt Presbyterſhip he miniſtred at <hi>Alexandria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. By his ſecond at <hi>Antioch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. He was under <hi>Zebenus</hi> the Biſhop at <hi>Antioch,</hi> he never aſſumed that degree of Miniſtery in the Church.</p>
               <p n="4">4. He was Catechiſt before, by the ordination of <hi>Demetrius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. In this is obſerveable, That the People of <hi>Antioch</hi> had the call of their Miniſters, and none aſſumed that Authority over them in thoſe days.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> ſpeaks nothing of the Diſcipline of the Church, but in his ſecond Apology made to <hi>Antonius Pius,</hi> at the end of it, in which he ſpeaks of the <hi>Praeſul</hi> and <hi>Praepoſitus, Lector</hi> and Deacons; but the Papiſts have ſo corrupted it, as that there is no uſe to be made of it, there is foiſted in it the carrying about of the Sacraments to the ſick, the Miniſter, not the Deacon, to collect the Alms of the Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Ignatius Ep. <hi>3.</hi> ad Magneſianos.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caeterum quoniam merui videre vos per Damam Deo dignum Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copum veſtrum, &amp; Preſbyteros Deo dignos, Baſſum &amp; Apollonium &amp; convivam meum Sotionem Diaconum.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:40358:7"/>
               <p>Here the Pretbyters are clearly by name expreſſed, who are onely two; if there had been more, he would not have left them out, and have named <hi>Sotion</hi> the Deacon: And in all his Epiſtles, when he writes of Presbytery, you are to underſtand the ſame number alway, no true Church having one more then another.</p>
               <p>Egiſippus. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nà cum Apoſtolis ſuſcepit eccleſiam adminiſtrandam frater Domini Jacobus, qui Juſtus ab omnibus cognominatus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which Apoſtles were <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> Gal. 2.9.</p>
               <p>Hence <hi>Irenaeus, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. writing of that <hi>Acts</hi> 15. <hi>Aſcendiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Paulus &amp; Barnabas Hieroſolimam ad alteros Apoſtolos propter hanc quaeſtionem, &amp; univerſa eccleſia conveniſſet in unum:</hi> Here he ſpeaks of the Apoſtles and Church, but not Elders, which ſhews the Apoſtles and Elders were the ſame perſons, though diverſly ſet out, as 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 6.1. <hi>An Elder and Witneſs,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 Tim. 1.11. <hi>An Apoſtle, a Teacher,</hi> which implyeth the ſame thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Tertul. de Pudicitia.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Apoſtoli emittunt ad eos qui jam ex Nationibus allegi caeperant, Viſum eſt Spiritui Sancto &amp; nobis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where he leaves out the word <hi>Elders,</hi> and mentions Apoſtles, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intimating, that the Apoſtles and Elders were the ſame men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Clemens <hi>of</hi> Rome, Ep. <hi>to</hi> James.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Proretae officium Epiſcopus impleat, Praeſbyteri Nautarum, Diaconi diſpenſatorum locum tenent, hi qui Catechizant Nautalogis conferan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, Epibatis autem totius fraternitatis multitudo ſit ſimilis.</hi> The reſt of his works (if this Epiſtle be not) is ſpurious, and this groſly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted: But here the Catechiſt and the Presbyters are diſtinct workers in the Goſpel work or Miniſtery, the Presbyters were not to Catechize.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Hyeren. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>37.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Per omnia haec Deus pater oſtenditur Spiritu quidem operante, filio vero adminiſtrante, patre vero comprobante, homine vero conſummante ad ſalutem.</hi> And after ſhews how it is done, ſaying, <hi>Diviſiones cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſmatum ſunt, idem autem Spiritus; diviſiones miniſteriorum, idem autem Dominus; diviſiones operationum ſunt, idem autem Deus qui operatur omnia in omnibus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The gifts ars ſaid to be the Spirits.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Miniſteries or execution of them, the Sons.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The operations which depend on the ſeveral gifts of Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt, Paſtor, Teacher, and their ſeveral teachings, are ſaid to be Gods or the Fathers.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:40358:8"/>4. Theſe all tend to perfect the Believer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Similitud. Hormae. Diſc. Paul. Similitud. <hi>8.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Nuncius Domini coronas juſſit afferri, allatae ſunt autem coronae velut ex Palmis factae, &amp; coronavit eos viros nuncius in quorum virgis Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinos invenerat &amp; fructum, &amp; juſſit eos ire in turrim: ſed &amp; illos vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros miſit in turrim in quorum virgis Pampinos invenerat ſine fructu, dato eis ſigillo, nam veſtem eandem habebant, id eſt, candidam ſicut ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vem, cum quâ jubebat ipſos ire in turrim. Nec minus &amp; eos qui red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diderant virgas ſuas ſicut acceperant virides, datâ eis veſte candidâ &amp; ſic eos dimiſit ire in turrim: his conſummatis ait ad Paſtorem il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum; ego vado, tu vero dimitte hos intra muros in eo loco quo quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> meruit habitare.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This Book is wonderfully corrupted throughout, yet many things thereof would ſerve to prove the things aſſerted, but this being clear and full, ſufficeth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Hieron. Ep. ad Evagrium.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Et ut ſciamus traditiones Apoſtolicas ſumptas de veteri Teſtamento, quod Aaron &amp; filii ejus at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Levitae in Templo fuerint, hoc ſibi E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopi Preſbyteri &amp; Diaconi in eccleſia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here he compares <hi>Aaron</hi> and his two Sons to the Evangeliſt, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor and Teacher (though I ſuppoſe the true order was broken before <hi>Hieroms</hi> time) and the Levites to the Deacons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregory</hi> is forced to confeſs the truth, though, as it were, againſt his will, 16 <hi>Hom. ſuper Ezek. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 72. <hi>Orientalis via tres hinc &amp; tres inde Thalamos habere memoratur: non inconvenienter acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pimus, ſi tres eſſe fidelium ordines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now as there are three Orders of Believers, ſo there were three Chambers or Meeting-places to meet in, and Miniſtery implyed, though then at <hi>Rome</hi> were no ſuch Order.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Policarp. Ep. ad Philippenſes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rogo igitur vos omnes inſistere verbo juſtitiae &amp; patientiae quam oculata fide vidiſtis non ſolum in beatiſſimis illis Ignatio ſcilicet, &amp; Zozimo &amp; Rufo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe three being the whole Church Miniſtery mentioned by <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cephor. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 29. <hi>Zozimus</hi> and <hi>Rufus</hi> were never Biſhops of <hi>Antioch,</hi> as in the Catalogue of the Biſhops appears.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The ground generally laid down for this threefold Miniſtery, is taken from the Trinity of perſons in that one Divine Eſſence of God.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:40358:8"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clem. Alex. Strom. Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 799. calls the three Aſſemblies of the Church, <hi>Beatam Sanctorum manſionum trinitatem,</hi> then by which it could not be expreſſed more fitly, commending it unto us in the higheſt myſtery, in whom they are indeed made one, to which Chriſt alludes, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. <hi>ver.</hi> 11, 21.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Dionyſius cap. <hi>5.</hi> de Eccleſ. Hierarch.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Et quidem Hierarchiam omnem in trinitatis diſtribuerimus nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And truly, ſaith he, we diſtribute all Hierarchy into the number of the Trinity, that is, of three.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Ignatius Ep. <hi>6.</hi> ad Philad.</head>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus Epiſcopus, una cum Preſbyterorum Collegio &amp; Diaconis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervis meis, quando quidem &amp; unus ingenitus Deus &amp; pater, &amp; unus unigenitus filius Deus verbum &amp; homo, unus paracletus Spiritus veritatis.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Hyren. Lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>75.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Per hanc ordinationem &amp; hujuſmodi convenientiam &amp; talis factus &amp; plaſmatus homo ſecundum imaginem &amp; ſimilitudinem infecti Dei, patre quidem bene ſentiente, filio vero miniſtrante &amp; formante, ſpiritu vero nutriente &amp; augente, homine vero paulatim proficiente &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniente ad perfectum.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6. Now as the Miniſters are three, ſo they had a threefold Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, which were diſtinguiſhed diverſly one from the other.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Clem. Alex. Lib. <hi>7.</hi> p. <hi>779.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Salutares hae converſiones pro ordine mutationis dividuntur &amp; temporibus, &amp; locis, &amp; honoribus, &amp; cognitionibus, &amp; haereditatibus, &amp; miniſteriis uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad eam quae tranſcendit contemplationem, &amp; eſt proxima Domino in aeternite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe ſaving converſions for order of change, are divided both in times, places, honors, knowledge, inheritances, miniſteries; and implieth, That the Saints in the Church came (in time) to change their Miniſtery, and with their Miniſtery, their former place of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, and had greater honor in the Church, and had a higher degree of knowledge miniſtred to them then formerly: So that it is clear, the ſame Doctrine was not preached by the Evangeliſt, that was by the Paſtor or Doctor; nor did they preach to the ſame people, or in the ſame place, as men dream. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. the Apoſtle ſpeaks of another mans life, which he would not boaſt of, that is, other mans Miniſtery.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:40358:9"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dionyſius Ep. Tito.</hi> divides the Miniſtery into <hi>Nutriens, Reno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vans, Perficiens Miniſterium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In his <hi>Eccleſ, Hierarch. Pontificalis ordo non perficere ſolum, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; illuminare &amp; purgare novit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sacerdotum vero virtus habet in ſe, illuminantem &amp; purgantem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verum qui inferiores ad praeſtantiora tranſire nequeunt, propterea quod fas illis non eſt ad iſtjuſmodi proſilire ſuperbiam.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Tertul. de Exhort. Caſtitatis.</head>
               <p>Si habes jus Sacerdotis in temetipſo ubi neceſſe eſt habeas, oportet etiam diſciplinam Sacerdotis ubi neceſſe ſit habere jus Sacerdotis: Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamus Tinguis, Digamus offers, quanto magis, &amp;c. <hi>of this more fully in my Letters ſent to the Aſſembly, printed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7. And then by degrees, as believers were fitted, they were paſſed from one Miniſtery to the other more perfect Miniſtery.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Dionyſius cap. <hi>5.</hi> Eccleſ. Hiſto.</head>
               <p>Iſta quidem Sacroſancta Lex eſt, ut per primam &amp; ſequentiam ad auguſtiſſimam illius ſubvehamur lucem, <hi>idem ibid. cap. 2.</hi> Rudis ex ſeipſo non ſtatim continenter hanc cupiet, vero ſenſim ac per gradus ad priora ſemper &amp; digniora at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad excellentiora conſcendit, ſic<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> perfectus ad ſupremum illum tandem divinum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ordinem gradu proficiente ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vehetur.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Clem. Alex. Lib. <hi>3.</hi> Pedag.</head>
               <p>Multa per aenigmata, multa per parabolas quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> poſſunt prodeſſe iis qui in ea incidunt: ſed non eſt meum inquit paedagogus hac docere, ſed magiſtro ad ſancta verba exponenda opus habemus, ad quem nobis eundum eſt; &amp; jam quidem tempus eſt mihi ceſſandi à paedogogia, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis autem audiendi Magiſtrum; cum is autem vos acceperit, in bona diſciplina eductos edocebit eloquia.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1. Hence it is clear, one Miniſtery ended in the other, and fitted for the other, and none taught the others Doctrine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2. Here</hi> Magiſtrum <hi>is put for</hi> Paſtorem; <hi>he taught the Doctrine of Milk in his</hi> Paedagogus, <hi>which was the Teachers office, is clear.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Tertul. de Reſurrect. carniss.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Num &amp; homo interior hic uti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> renovari habebit per ſuggeſtum ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus, proficiens fide &amp; diſciplina die ac die; non illic, id eſt, non poſt reſurrectionem, ubi non uti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> die ac die renovare habemus, ſed ſemel ad ſummum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. He ſhews the renovation of the inward man ſpoken of, is to be in this life.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:40358:9"/>2. That it is to be day by day.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is by a proficiency in Faith.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This proficiency of Faith muſt have with it alſo a proficiency in Diſcipline day by day miniſtred to it, that it may grow in Faith accordingly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clem. Alex. Lib.</hi> 7. illuſtrates this by a ſweet Simile, <hi>At<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> àdeo uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad nos ipſos alii ſub alios ſunt collocati, quomodo ergo vel minima pars ferri unà monetur ſpiritu lapidis magnetis, extenſa per multos an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulos ferreos; ita etiam qui ſunt virtute praediti, Domino ſpiritu at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracti, cum prima manſione conjunguntur, deinceps autem alii uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad poſtremam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſeventh Book I ſuppoſe was written to perfect men; and ſignifieth that ſome are placed in the firſt Order, others of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, even to our ſelves of the third Manſion: therefore as a ſmall piece of Iron moved by the ſpirit of a Load-ſtone, drawn through many ſmall Iron Rings; ſo alſo they that are indued with vertue, are drawn by the Lords Spirit, when they are joyned in the firſt Manſion, then to the other, unto the third and laſt Manſion.</p>
               <p>A clearer proof of the practice of the Church, I ſuppoſe, cannot be brought, by which the Church-Government is to be exerciſed amongſt us; and before this be done, it is unpoſſible that the Saints ſhould thrive by any means miniſtred unto them in that confuſed way of Antichriſtian Diſcipline amongſt us at preſent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dionyſius Areop. cap.</hi> 6. <hi>p. prima,</hi> the whole Chapter ſhews this.</p>
               <p>Theſe three Miniſteries, and their ſeveral operations, are in an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect maner, according to the imperfect eſtate of the Church, thus touched by <hi>Tertul. de Corona.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alia eſt conditio, &amp;c. ut illorum quos Johannes admittebat ad la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacrum, ut centurionum fideliſſimorum quos Chriſtus probat, quos Petrus Catechizat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this there is a threefold act given to theſe three, which are to be exerciſed by the Miniſtery to every Chriſtian, Catechizing, Baptizing, and the approbation of the Evangeliſt in Baptizing. Hence <hi>Ignatius Ep.</hi> to <hi>Philadelp.</hi> That none ſhould be Baptized without the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the Biſhop, <hi>Non licet ſine Epiſcopo baptizare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the ſame Epiſtle he divides the threefold Society thus;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sine ipſis eccleſia electa non eſt,</hi> the Evangeliſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Collectio Sanctorum,</hi> the Paſtors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Congregatio Sancta,</hi> the Doctors Society.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:40358:10"/>
               <p>And to this purpoſe it is, that the Apoſtles call in the Goſpel thoſe miniſtred in the Goſpel with them, <hi>Fellow-laborers, co-workers, and helpers in the Goſpel;</hi> the one Catechizing the people without, the other admitting them into the Church, by Baptiſm; another, exhorting, and exerciſing their gifts to fit them for that Miniſtery, perfected them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cyp. Ep.</hi> 10. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>A primordio Epiſcopatus mei ſtatuerim ſine conſilio veſtro, id eſt, Compreſbyterorum, &amp; ſine conſenſu plebis, meâ privatim ſententiâ gerere nihil.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Dionyſius cap. <hi>2.</hi> Eccleſ. Hierarch.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deinde Sacros omnes gradus ſibi cooperentur, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cypr. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 4. calls <hi>Felix</hi> and <hi>Sabinus, Coepiſcopi;</hi> and after, <hi>Quod &amp; factum videmus in Sabini Collegae noſtri ordinatione;</hi> the word <hi>Collega</hi> is the ſame with <hi>Pauls</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: and though it is thought that thoſe <hi>Coepiſcopi,</hi> a word fit for the whole Church Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, were Biſhops of diverſe Societies; eſpecially reading in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his Epiſtles, where he is ſaid to have many Colleagues, which may be corruptions inſerted by the Papiſts: Thus we ſee what cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions are in <hi>Ignatius</hi> Epiſtles, multitudes of officers and offices inſerted, that were never thought on; and ſo in <hi>Cyprians</hi> much more.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Ep.</hi> 9. he ſpeaks of his own Colleagues and Rogations alſo: It is my opinion, That no Book extant is more corrupted, then <hi>Cyprians,</hi> of his time, for the Church was ſtrangely corrupted; he yet in many things retains ſome Principles of the true Church, and wrote more clearly of them then others of his time; though I confeſs, after the Two hundred years, the face of the Church was ſo changed, as that it was not to be known about which time he lived: and it is plain, he retained the Apoſtles term, which few after him do, and it were ſtrange if he did no more but that.</p>
               <p>Here I ſuppoſe it will not be unneceſſary to ſet down an Anſwer, uſually made by many, to thoſe enquire the Reaſon, Why the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es are not conſtituted as they were in the Apoſtles, rnd immediately after; they ſay, The Church was then in its Infancy, which was the onely grand ground of Apoſtacy, at the firſt, of men from the truth, as if the firſt form in the Goſpel were not the beſt, and the patern for future times, as <hi>Moſes</hi> patern in the Mount for him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ambroſe</hi> on Epheſ. 4. <hi>At ubi autem omnia loca circumplexa eſt eccleſia, Conventicula ſunt constituta, &amp; rectores &amp; caetera officia
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40358:10"/> in eccleſiis ſunt ordinata, ut nullus de clero auderet qui ordinatus non eſſet, praeſumere officium quod ſciret non ſibi creditum vel conceſſum, &amp; caepit alia ordine &amp; providentia gubernari eccleſia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>More then this need not be ſaid to prove the practice of the then Church, and how then of the after Churches, and the Churches for ſome time before, upon this Atheiſtical Antichriſtian ground to be in the form totally ſubverted; ſo that the form of Church-Government then and for ſome time before, cannot be brought to prove, or war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant any now, the true form of the Goſpel being deſtroyed; nor was it ſcarce known which was indeed the hiding of the Church; no wonder if it be a hidden thing to us: he ſaith in this place, <hi>Omnes docebant, omnes baptizabant,</hi> he ſaith, They obſerved not the time, nor faſted before Baptiſm, nor had <hi>Peter</hi> any Deacons at <hi>Cornelius</hi> houſe to Baptize, as if the Deacons office was onely to Baptize, he not minding that ſome of the ſeven may be with him and Baptize; in all which he corruptly quarrels with the Apoſtles practice, as if they had found a better form to ſerve God by, then that of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; which the Biſhops of the times preceeding did correct, and like the carnal Gentiles, ſeeking to be wiſe, became fools; and like the fooliſh woman in the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> pull'd down the Houſe of God with both their hands, and worſe then ſhe, ſet up a Cage for unclean birds of their own, predicted by <hi>Zech.</hi> 5.8, 9. But of this in its place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ignatius Ep.</hi> to <hi>Policarpus,</hi> He writing to <hi>Policarpus,</hi> mentions the Presbytery, and ſaith, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nà laborate, inter vos unà certate, unà currite, &amp;c. ut diſpenſatores, &amp; aſſeſſores, &amp; miniſtri Dei.</hi> In the word Diſpencers, the admiſſion of members to Ordinances is ſignified; in Aſſeſſors, their Government in general intended; in Miniſters, their teaching.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The Church was governed by theſe three conjunctly in Eccleſiaſtical things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ignatius to Trallis.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>It is neceſſary, whatever ye do, ye go about nothing (that is of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical publike concernment) without the Biſhop; but alſo, that ye ſubmit to the Presbytery, as to the Apoſtles of Jeſus Chriſt. In theſe is the Church true Presbytery; onely and alone in theſe the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod and Colledge of Miniſtery is exiſtent, and in none other. Other Authority is Antichriſtian, and tends to oppreſſion of the Saints.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertull.</hi> in the forecited place <hi>de Exhortatione Caſtitatis, Honor
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40358:11"/> per ordinis conſeſſum ſanctificatus, adeò ubi non eſt eccleſiaſtici ordinis conſeſſus, &amp; Offers, &amp; Tinguis, &amp; Sacerdos, &amp;c.</hi> before he ſaith theſe have <hi>Eccleſiae aucthoritas,</hi> the Church authority.</p>
               <p>This is <hi>Conſeſſus Eccleſiaeſtici ordinis</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and any other Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical convent, then this Juridical is not according to the Primitive Church and Goſpel-frame; this was the true Presbytery, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then theſe are ſpurious and falſe.</p>
               <p>To this well agreeth that of <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.19. that if two of you agree on earth, &amp;c. The Church, while it was according to the Goſpel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, governed by theſe three, it was called, <hi>The pillar and ground of Truth;</hi> but when that fell, and Miniſters of other Societies ruled, then came the corruption of the Church, the Lord not approving of them, as is well obſerved in the Preface of the Bibles written <hi>To the Reader,</hi> printed in King <hi>James</hi>'s days: yet for all that, the learned knew, That certain worthy men have been brought to untimely death for no other fault, but for ſeeking to reduce their countrey-men to good order and diſcipline; and that in ſome Common-weals it was made a capital crime, once to motion the making of a new Law, for the abrogating of an old, though the ſame were moſt pernicious; and that certain which would be accounted pillars of the State, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns of vertue and prudence, could not be brought for a long time to give way to good letters and refined ſpeech, but bare themſelves as averſe from them, as from Rocks and boxes of Poyſon: And he was no babe, viz. <hi>Greg. Theol.</hi> but a great <hi>Cler.</hi> that gave forth, and in writing to poſterity (in paſſion peradventure) That he had not ſeen any profit to come by any Synod or Meeting of the Clergy, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the contrary. By ſaying it was in paſſion, was a good plaiſter for ſuch a dangerous ſore. He ſhews what the Councels before him, he living about 380. did; and indeed God ordained, That not many together, but ſeven men of ſeveral ages, ſignified by the ſeven Angels, are onely to reſtore the faln Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hieron.</hi> 1 <hi>Cap. ad Titum.</hi> ſaith, When Presbyters governed, <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae cura aequaliter inter plures dividebatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this may be applyed that of <hi>Egiſippus,</hi> cited by <hi>Euſebius, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nà cum Apoſtolis ſuſcepit Eccleſiam adminiſtrandam frater Domini Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobus, qui juſtus ab omnibus cognominatus.</hi> This was underſtood of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> Gal. 2.9. and not of all the Apoſtles: <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> miniſtred to the Gentiles; <hi>James</hi> the leſs was ſlain, before he took this Government, by <hi>Herod:</hi> So that it is without queſtion,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40358:11"/> here is onely meant the three Apoſtles, who were <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Peter</hi> calls himſelf, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 6.1. according to the form of Government in the other Goſpel Churches, they being not differing one from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other in form of Government, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> being the patern or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church. This Book is ſaid to contain Apoſtolical Traditions, but is loſt, and a counterfeit left in its place, <hi>Nicephor. Eccl. Hiſt. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 26.</p>
               <p n="9">9. As the Miniſters, ſo the People were diſtinguiſhed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anthanaſius</hi> cites <hi>Theognoſtus</hi> in his Tract. <hi>de verbis Evang. Matthei cap.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 31. <hi>quicun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> dixerit, &amp;c. Qui ſemel at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> iterum terminos praetergreſſus oſt, minus feret ſupplicii; qui vero tertio contempſerit, nullam veniam conſequi poteſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here, by the bounds of the Church, I underſtand the threefold So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties of the Saints; under the third whereof, if any contemned, there was no pardon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Athanaſius primum &amp; ſecundum terminos appellat Catecheſin, hoc eſt initiationem de patre &amp; filio; tertium vero qui eſt in conſummatione myſteriorum, &amp; ſermone; qui traditur in communicatione ſpiritus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſhews the Government was much hid in <hi>Athanaſius</hi> time; he ſaith, Catechizing was initiation, which was not; but in Baptiſm un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Doctors Miniſtery was initiation, and not under the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſts Miniſtery: And then he ſaith, In Catechizing were to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the two firſt bounds, which was but one part of Miniſtery, and that not of the Church neither; without doubt <hi>Theognoſtus</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4, 5, 6.</p>
               <p>He is more clear in that which followeth, <hi>Verum ex his nequaquam aliquis dicere poterit, quod doctrina ſpiritus excellentior ſit doctrina filii, ſed filius ſeſe dimittat ad imbecillitatem imperfectorum, ſpiritus autem ſignaculum eſt eorum qui perfecti ſunt: proinde non irremiſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis &amp; incondonabilis eſt blasphemia in spiritum, quòd ſpiritus major eſt filio, ſed quod imperfectis detur venia, iis vero qui guſtaverunt coeleste donum, qui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> perfecti ſunt, nulla relinquatur ad veniam excuſatio, aut paenae excuſatio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Here are three bounds expreſſed of the Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In theſe the Saints are divided according to their gifts, in one the imperfect, the other the perfect.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In <hi>Athanſius</hi> time theſe bounds were deſtroyed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. He alludes theſe three Manſions to the Trinity, making that the ground of them, as the other before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dioniſius</hi> diſtinguiſheth them by theſe names, <hi>Rudes, illuminati, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecti.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:40358:12"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Simil. Herm.</hi> 9. <hi>Omnos enim infantes honorati ſunt apud Dominum, &amp; primi habentur;</hi> and after, <hi>Hi omnes candidi juvenes ſunt, qui credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derunt &amp; qui credituri ſunt, ex eodem enim genere ſunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And being a Paſtor, mentions not the ſociety of Fathers, alluding to 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.14. unleſs the copy be corrupted, or they cloſely intended <hi>in lapidibus rotundis,</hi> of theſe he ſaith, <hi>Hi omnes de candido monte ſunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertul. de Praeſcrip. Haeret.</hi> ſhewing how the Hereticks by their wiles corrupted the Church, ſaith, <hi>De ſcripturis aguni, &amp; de ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ſuadent;</hi> and after, <hi>in ipſo vero congreſſu firmos quidem fatigant, infirmos capiunt, medios cum ſcrupulo dimittunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clemens</hi> ſaith of the children or Doctors Society, <hi>Non enim nos pueri &amp; infantes appellati ſumus, quòd ſit puerilis &amp; contemnenda no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra diſciplina, ut nos calumniati ſunt qui inflati ſunt ſcientia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Strom. l. 1. <hi>Parvuli ergo ſunt etiam philoſophi, niſi à Chriſtò viri fiunt,</hi> he calls them, <hi>Primogeniti qui deſcripti in coelis ſunt,</hi> becauſe their Names written after Baptiſm in the Church Rolls, alluding to that <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.23. He calls the other Church members, youth and perfect men, <hi>Germani</hi> and <hi>amici Dei, Athletae, perfecti Dei alumni.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vatablus,</hi> Pſal. 84.8. <hi>De</hi> turma ad turmam, <hi>de</hi> cumulo ad cumulum, <hi>vel de</hi> caterva ad catervam, <hi>comparebit quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eorum apud Deum, &amp;c. id est, ad ſingulas catervas accedent, ut audiant laudes Dei, vel ibunt turmatim donec videant Deum, &amp;c. vel apparuerint coram eo in Sion, ac ſi diceret, nunquam quieſcent donec pervenient ad Templum ipſum, ubi Deus ſuper arcam conspicitur. Quidam vertunt, ibunt de virtute in virtutem, videbitur Deus in Sion: alii, de</hi> doctrina in doctrinam, <hi>vel de</hi> academia in academiam, <hi>id est, creſcet illorum doctrina àdeo ut unuſquiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> videat eam in eccleſia: aut creſcet donec perveniant ad pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectam Dei notitiam. Doctoris magis placet illa verſio, de</hi> virtute in virtutem, <hi>id est, Collectis inde novis viribus donec appareat illis Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus in Sion.</hi> Without queſtion in theſe words the Goſpel-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is aymed at, and ſweetly ſet out, when things ſhall be made more clear unto us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clem. Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Strom. p.</hi> 811. <hi>Mihi quidem videtur eſſe prima quaedam ſalutaris mutatio quae fuit à Gentibus ad fidem, ut prius dixi, ſecunda eſt à fide in cognitionem</hi> 3 <hi>illa vero trajiciens ad charitatem;</hi> a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold change clearly expreſt, as in words they may, and that matter and way by which, and unto which, as excellently ſet down.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dionyſius cap.</hi> 6, <hi>Eccleſ. Hiſtor.</hi> ſeems to mention a ceremonial practice in uſe in the Church, at the changing of Societies, by a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40358:12"/> change of Garments, alluding unto <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.10, 12, 13.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prioris autem veſtis poſitio, alteriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> aſſumptio, migrationem il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam à media vita (licet ſacra) ad perfectiorem ſignificat; ſicut in Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na regeneratione promotionem indicabat à purgata vita, ad contemplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, illuminantem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> habitum illa veſtis condentis immutatio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Clem. Strom. lib. 7. p. 817. <hi>Sunt enim quomodo Gymnicis certamini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, ita etiam in eccleſia coronae virorum &amp; puerorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Field</hi> obſerves, there were in ancient <hi>Rome,</hi> certain Churches called <hi>Baptiſmal Churches,</hi> becauſe in them onely Baptiſm was origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally miniſtred, and not in all. <hi>Vid. Potter,</hi> of 666. <hi>cap.</hi> 17. <hi>p.</hi> 114.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clem. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 810. <hi>Cum ceſſaverint quidem à purgatione, ceſſave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint etiam ab alio miniſterio, &amp; ſic ſit ſanctum &amp; inter ſanctos: deindo iis qui ſunt mundo corde per proximam Domino adhaeſionem perpetuae contemplationi permanet reſtitutio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12. When the Church was taking her leave of the world, ſets down the full Eccleſiaſtical Officers, called by <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> fitly <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is more then any ſince, that I have read, have done.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nunc autem ſeptem Diaconos eſſe oportet, aliquantos Preſbyteros, ut bini ſint per eccleſias, &amp; unus in civitate Epiſcopus:</hi> in which he ſhews what the Eccleſiaſtical officers, in every Goſpel Church, ought to be at the departure of the Church, he living about 380. as which he ſheweth are to be ſeven Deacons, two Presbyters, and one Biſhop in a city.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ambroſ.</hi> on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.31. <hi>Ye may all Propheſie one by one;</hi> ſhews, how they were diſtinguiſhed in their general Meetings in their maner of ſitting, which Meetings by <hi>Dionyſius</hi> is fitly called <hi>Synaxis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Haec traditio Synagogae eſt, quam vos vult ſectari; quia Chriſtianis quidem ſcripſit, ſed ex Gentibus factis, non à Judoeis: ut ſedentes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputent ſeniores dignitate</hi> (not in age) <hi>in Cathedris, ſequentes in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelliis, noviſſimi in pavimento, ſuper Mattas, quibus ſi revelatum fuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit dandum locum dicendi praecepit, nec deſpiciendos, quia membra cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris ſunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is a Tradition of the Synagogue, which he will have us to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, becauſe he hath written it to Chriſtians, but done of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, not of the Jews; That the Seniors in dignity ſhould diſpute ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in Chairs, thoſe next them on Forms, the laſt upon Mats on the the pavement; to whom, if any thing were revealed, he requireth that they ſhould have leave to ſpeak, and not to be deſpiſed becauſe they are members of the body.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:40358:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>1. He confeſſeth this order of placing members in this their general Church-meeting, to be derived from the Jewiſh Synagogue; but the exerciſe here required of the Gentiles was ſuch, as the Jews in their Synagogues practiſed not.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He proves ſufficiently this oft to be the Chriſtian Church pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, becauſe written to the Gentiles.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Here are onely three ſorts of people mentioned; the firſt where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are Seniors, yet not <hi>ſenectute,</hi> but <hi>dignitate,</hi> not in age, but dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; the laſt ſort, ſome of them that ſate on Maps, may be of fuller age then thoſe ſate in Chairs: This being one of the diſtinctions made by <hi>Clemens</hi> among the Church members, <hi>Dignitatibus,</hi> p. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> and theſe are Elders indeed, and no man is to deſpiſe their youth, but honor them for their gifts ſake. Now this being the means they had to try the ability of their members, to fit them for the ſucceeding Miniſtery, it was permitted to any to ſpeak; and gives the Reaſon, Becauſe they are members: by which he ſhews theſe were none, but ſuch as were of Church communion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ap.</hi> Of this may be fitly this, That as in the natural man there are differing ſtatures, according to which men are differenced and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored; ſo in the Spiritual there are differing ſtatures, according to which, Chriſt hath in the Goſpel differenced them, and appointed them ſo to be in the Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It ſheweth, <hi>Fleſh and blood ſhall not inherit the kingdom of God;</hi> ſo that men cannot inherit it by prerogatives thence, or accordingly thereunto <hi>(durus ſermo)</hi> or in conſideration of any thing thereof: Man, as natural, hath nothing to do therein at all.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hence the condition propounded to all, old and yong, rich and poor, is, That unleſs they become as little children, ſit among them, learn among them, &amp;c. bearing the image of the heavenly Infancy of Chriſt, as of <hi>Adam,</hi> they cannot enter the kingdom of heaven, that is, the Churches Society, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.49. he that cannot deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in this, is not fit for the kingdom.</p>
               <p>That we may ſee we are not left onely to this Traditional Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition onely, but that we have Divine Authority more fully to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the ſame by, ſee <hi>James</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 1, 7.</p>
               <p>The Objections are many againſt this, the Scriptures abounds with as many Anſwers. The Objections may be reduced to two chief heads.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Do ye think old men will be made children, and ſit with chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and endure to ſit with them?</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:40358:13"/>2. Will rich men ſit on Mats, and poor men ſit in Chairs? what diſhonor were this to greatneſs?</p>
               <p n="1">1. This is one thing makes the entrance into the Kingdom ſo dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.17. <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.23.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God reſpects not any mans perſon for his greatneſs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is according to the will of God, that goodneſs in his preſence ſhould be honored, not riches.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Hence the richeſt man of the world cannot be Chriſts diſciple, unleſs he thus deny himſelf.</p>
               <p>But to the Scripture, <hi>James</hi> 2.1.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is neceſſary to let you know, That this Epiſtle was written to men out of Church ſociety, as this we are in, whoſe meetings the Church Order or Diſcipline was not obſerved, in which greatneſs, not goodneſs, was looked on.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Apoſtle reproves this corruption in the Jews, and tells them, This was an injury offered to the faith of Chriſt, which is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of more honor then any thing elſe, and make a man more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable before God, though not before the world.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He ſhews in Church Diſcipline, no reſpect of perſons is of God to be permitted.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That in Church-meetings, before God onely, faith is had in eſteem; and to be honored ſo, that the way of the Church, and of God, are quite contrary to the world and our Church-way, which is according to the world, and not the word.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 2. 1. He ſhews in whom it was done, in two men exemplarily.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Where it was done, and that was, in their Synagogue.</p>
               <p n="3">3. How it was, and that was, by placing one in a place of note, a chair, and the other on the Mat at his footſtool.</p>
               <p n="4">4. For what the one hath his good place, and that is, for his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel, and gold Ring; and the other is placed meanly, becauſe he have no better clothes.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In which God reproves all carnal reſpect in Spiritual things, either to diſeſteem the godly, becauſe poor, or to honor others in the Church, becauſe rich.</p>
               <p>Here let no man think, that I write this to ſhadow the greatneſs or Authority of any in the Common-weal, to whom God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands (for conſcience) obedience of his people, they having their Authority and Inſtitution from God, for the good, peace and weal of the State in which we live.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:40358:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 4. God condemns them for partiality: and,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 5. Oppoſes the riches of the Saint, to the natural mans riches, and ſaith, He is rich in faith, far exceeding worldly goods; and tells them, They are alſo choſen of God, though they condem them, and imply, That it is a grievous thing before God, in Gods houſe to ſet up earthly glory, and depoſe that that is the glory of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which thing is not according to God nor godlineſs: And then tells them, The poor are heirs of the kingdom, and that the place and honor thereof may belong to them as to any other, and to take it from him, is to rob him of his inheritance, as to take a rich mans poſſeſſions were to rob him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 7. He ſhews them their error, by repreſenting the ungodly practice of graceleſs great men; and thence ſhews how unfit they were to be honored in the Church: 1. They were perſecutors of thoſe believers, drawing them before Judgement-ſeats. 2. They blaſphemed that worthy name by which they were called, by railing againſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing and condemning Godlineſs to the world; 1. As to the Church, that they give honor to none in the Church, until they have that in them makes them honorable, for the honor in the Church cometh from God firſt. 2. Not to diſhonor God or Godlineſs in a poor man for his poverty. 3. To Chriſtians, not to imitate the Phariſees in their corruptions, by ſeeking to have the chief places in Synagogues, but to be content with that place Chriſt the Lord of the Church ſhall place thee in. It is illuſtrated <hi>Luke</hi> 14.8, 10. when called to a wedding (that is, to the Society of Chriſt in the Goſpel) ſit not down <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the chief place, <hi>v.</hi> 10. but ſit down <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the loweſt, leſt one more honorable then thou, &amp;c. I believe, that were the Jewiſh cuſtoms known better of us then they are, many Goſpel myſteries would be unfolded, which now are hid: the variety of words imply a diverſity of matter intended, as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, by which God reveals, that we without the Jews ſhall not be made perfect, God will again come to honor that people to the world in theſe and many other things: But the Scripture ſhews, That a man muſt firſt ſit in the loweſt place, and continue there until called higher; that is, to the higher means of grace, when he ſhould have honor of all. I may ſay of this Scripture, as the Apoſtle of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, <hi>Doth God take care of Oxen?</hi> ſo doth God take care of feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; onely here in feaſting was but the bark, the Church order, the pith, though I do not ſay; but it ſerves to direct men in that alſo,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40358:14"/> which is as the ſhell to the kernel. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.9. makes a ſweet applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe things to the poor, That though they were poor in the world, yet by grace came to be exalted above worldly advancements. <hi>Ver.</hi> 10. the rich they are exhorted to rejoyce, in that they are made low, that they have a heart to become children, to ſee grace in a poor Saint, ſet up above greatneſs in himſelf, and his heart not oppoſe it; <hi>For its hard for a rich man to enter into the kingdom of heaven:</hi> and, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. <hi>Not many rich, not many wiſe,</hi> &amp;c. ſo that the mercy is the greater to thoſe rich men are called, and thus indowed with an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble minde, and nature thus overcome in them by grace.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.41. <hi>Tertul.</hi> in his book <hi>de Reſurrectione carnis,</hi> applyeth, <hi>There is one glory of the ſun, another of the moon, another of the ſtars,</hi> to the differing eſtates of the Saints in the Church; but if not to them, if to the Saints in heaven, it ſhews that there's an agreement between the glory of Saints in heaven, and thoſe in earth; thoſe of the third Manſion, of men, ſhine as the Sun, thoſe of the ſecond, of youth, as the Moon, thoſe of the firſt, as Stars: Whence is great matter of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to be miniſtred to men to grow in grace, and to contend for perfection in the Church for this life, for that to come, whereas in our Societies there is none at all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertul.</hi> in the ſame book hath excellently diſtinguiſhed them, had not the enemies of truth labored to obſcure it, ſaying, <hi>Non omnis caro eſt eadem caro, non ad denegandum ſubſtantiae communionem, ſed praero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gativae peraequationem, corpus honoris non generis in differentiam redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens, in hoc &amp; figurata ſubjicit exempla animalium &amp; elementorum, alia caro hominis, id eſt, ſervi Dei qui vere homo eſt, alia Jumenti, id eſt, Ethnici, de quò propheta, Adſimilatus eſt homo irrationalibus Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis: alia caro volucrum, id eſt, Martyrum, alia caro piſcium, id eſt, quibus aquâ baptiſmatis ſufficit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here <hi>Caro volucrum</hi> ſhould be for <hi>Martyrum (Juvenum)</hi> for <hi>Tertul.</hi> applyeth it to the differing eſtate of the general Church Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties, and then the compariſon ſweetly agrees with the Church and the world <hi>Ethnick,</hi> to which it is compared; but the words fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing abundantly clear it, <hi>Ad diſciplinam totam hoc dirigit</hi> (now Martyrdom pertains not to Church diſcipline) <hi>ut hic dicat portandam imaginem Chriſti in iſta carne in juſto tempore diſciplinae.</hi> Mark it well, in juſt time of diſcipline, applying to the times of infancy, of youth, and Chriſtian man-age, according to the order of Chriſtian di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline in the Church, and not natural growth. Again, for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40358:15"/> of the ſtudy and endeavor of theſe children of Error to pervert the right ways of God, for which they had leave of God to accompliſh his own purpoſe, for the hiding of the Church, and proves the way to be the true way, becauſe they endeavored ſo much to hide it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertul. de praeſcr. Haeret. Quid ergo ſi Epiſcopus, ſi Diaconus, ſi vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dua, ſi virgo, ſi Doctor, ſi etiam Martyr lapſus à regula fuerit? ideo hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſes veritatem videbuntur obtinere? ex perſonis probamus fidem, an ex fide perſonas?</hi> 1. Here is <hi>vidua</hi> and <hi>Diaconus,</hi> before <hi>Doctor;</hi> and in ſtead of Paſtor, <hi>virgo</hi> put in, a meer plain Popiſh foiſt, and no way countenanced of the truth. 2. I ſuppoſe, as <hi>virgo,</hi> ſo <hi>Martyr</hi> is alſo added, to make the confuſion the greater: For how can a man be a Martyr, as that word is uſually taken, and fall from the Rule; in which is to be ſeen, how unprofitable the writing of the Ancients are in themſelves, what diligent care is to be taken in them, and how uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs without the Word unto us. 3. If this be not aſſented to, how can the whole Church officers be mentioned in this place, as intended by the Author? ſo that there is a putting in and putting out, and inver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of order clearly ſeen in it: and this was practiſed before <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians</hi> days, but much more after, appears by the Obteſtation placed by <hi>Hyrenaeus,</hi> at the end of a book, now loſt, <hi>Adjuro te qui tranſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis librum iſtum per Dominum Jeſum Chriſtum, &amp; per glorioſum ejus adventum, quò judicaturus eſt vivos &amp; mortuos; ut conferas poſtquam tranſcripſeris, &amp; emendes illum ad exemplar unde ſcripſiſti diligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſime, hanc quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> obteſtationem ſimiliter transferas ut juvenisti in exemplari.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. Now that the people were thus in Miniſtery, and places ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily divided, and at the adminiſtration of the Sacraments were to meet together, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.20. appears.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Ignatius Ep. <hi>to</hi> Philadelp.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus etiam panis pro omnibus confractus est, &amp; unus calix totius eccleſiae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That this Epiſtle is ancient, appears from the allowance of the Cup to the whole Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clem. Alex.</hi> tells, Thoſe were newly ingrafted into the Church, they were not to enjoy mean things, onely as they looked on them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>At vero augustior illa unius ejuſdem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> &amp; panis &amp; calicis communis pacifita que communio, concordiae illis ut fratribus unà educatis Divinas ſtatuit leges.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:40358:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dionyſius</hi> only ſhews the manner how it was to be communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the members of the ſeveral Societies <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>de Eccl. Hist. Elementíſque</hi> (which are the Sacramental bread and wine) <hi>illius ad inferiora &amp; ſecunda proceſſus, finem facit diviniorem, ad pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma &amp; principaliora redditum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Here are three Societies expreſſed in the inferiour, ſecond and firſt. 2. With his elements of bread and wine he comes to the children, and then proceeds to the ſecond, the young men; and returning, ends at the firſt and more principall Society of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. How full and cleer this teſtimony is, I leave to all to judge, ſeeing it is the childrens bread, but not the <hi>Catechumeni,</hi> they were not baptized, nor had any part in the Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</p>
               <p n="11">11. That the ſeverall Societies under the ſeverall Miniſters were one Church, appears.</p>
               <p>Ignat. Ep. 5. ad Philadelph.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gaudium ſempiternum eſt &amp; ſingulare, maximè iis quî ſunt in unum cum Epiſcopo, cum Preſbyteris &amp; Diaconis probatis in vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntate Dei Patris, per Dominum Jeſum Chriſtum. (In unum,</hi> that is, <hi>in unum corpus,</hi> in one body.</p>
               <p>This order was glanced at by <hi>Baſil. de Sp. Sanct.</hi> but I doubt not practiſed in the Church he living about 370.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Profectò ſtulti &amp; omnino infantilis animi, eſt puerí<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> cui revera lacte opus eſt, ignorare magnum illud neceſſarium ſalutis, quod quemadmodum doctores facere ſolent in inſtituendis diſcipulis; ita nos in exercitatione pietatis, dum ad perfectionem inducimur, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum perceptu facilioribus ac noſtro modulo congruentibus, ad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſibilem ſcientiam paulatim introducti fuimus, &amp;c.</hi> then after gives the reaſon, <hi>ne protinus ſpectaculo purae lucis offenſi cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garemus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Gregor. Niſſen 380 <hi>An.</hi> de orat. pauper.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quemadmodum hi pueros è parentum manibus ſuſceptos adhuc in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantes &amp; balbutientes, non protinus abditis diſciplinarum praeceptioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus onerant; ſed primò literarum formas inſculpunt in ceris, earúmque nomina declarant, &amp; ipſorum manus per impreſſos illos literarum du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus agunt, &amp; exercent mox illos, ad cognitionem ſyllabarum pervehunt, atque ita deinceps ad verborum expreſſionem perducunt; ſit etiam Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae duces initio documenta quaedam quae ſunt inſtar elementorum au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditoribus proponunt: Deinceps, gradatim ea quae perfectiora magíſque recondita ſunt patefaciunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:40358:16"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jerem Ep.</hi> to <hi>Marcell.</hi> ſhews a ſtrange confuſion to be in his time in the government of the Church, <hi>An.</hi> 370.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Epiſcopus tertius eſt apud Montaniſtas, habent primos de</hi> Pepuſa Phrygiae <hi>Patriarchas, ſecundos quos Canones appellant; atque ita in tertium, id eſt, penè ultimum locum Epiſcopi devolvuntur.</hi> And then after of the Biſhops (who among the Montaniſts were degraded) thus, <hi>Locum Apoſtolorum tenent apud nos.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which ſhews, 1. In theſe times ſome Churches retained ſome more likeneſſe of the Goſpel form then other, though the true form was not obſerved by <hi>Jerom.</hi> 2. It is like ſome Church might retain the true form in thoſe times, but condemned for He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks and Schiſmaticks, they not obſerving the Decrees of the Councels of theſe times.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> divides the Miniſtry, as is obſerved by <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> on the Ep. to the <hi>Rom.</hi> which is very remarkably done in his Salutation to the Romans; whom he ſalutes not in the beginning of the Epiſtle as others in the other Epiſtles; but in the laſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; the form whereof was not changed without cauſe of note.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Evangeliſts Society, <hi>ch.</hi> 16. <hi>ver.</hi> 5. in which he ſalutes the houſe of <hi>Aquila,</hi> and the church therein.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How appears this to be the Evangeliſts Society?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R.</hi> 1. He calls that Society the Church Synecdochi <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He calls <hi>Aquila my helper,</hi> (not ours, as uſually, and after as he ſaith of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi>) ſignifying he did at <hi>Rome</hi> what <hi>Paul</hi> was to do had he been there, or that he did do when he was there.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj. Priſcilla</hi> is ſaid to help <hi>Paul</hi> alſo with <hi>Aquila:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was in Tent-making, not in Church-edification.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R.</hi> 1. <hi>Ver.</hi> 3. They are ſaid to be his helpers in Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> as thoſe women <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which was a work required of all, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.17. with one ſpirit ſtriving together: and this was a private perſwading of men or women to imbrace the doctrine <hi>Paul</hi> taught in publick, as <hi>Act.</hi> 18.16. which was not a miniſteriall work.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Paul</hi> in this would honour <hi>Priſcilla</hi> in <hi>Aquila;</hi> giving ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to her as to the weaker veſſel.</p>
               <p>But the chief grounds proving this Society to be the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts are, 1 From thoſe hee ſalutes, which were of that Society doubtleſſe, from the commendation given them for their eminency of gifts. <hi>Epinetus</hi> is the firſt fruits of <hi>Achaia; Mary</hi> laboured
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40358:16"/> much on them; <hi>Andronicus</hi> and <hi>Junia</hi> were in Chriſt before <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf; and then ſalutes <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the chatechiſt, an helper with <hi>Aquila,</hi> which was a member of that Society; <hi>Apelles</hi> approved, <hi>Stachys</hi> and <hi>Amplias</hi> my beloved ones.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hee comes to ſalute the other Societies, having done with the Evangeliſts, and begins with thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> where is to be underſtood for perfecting the ſenſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, thoſe of the brethren of <hi>Aristobulus</hi> Society, <hi>ver.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Ver.</hi> 11. Salute thoſe of the brethren of <hi>Narciſſus</hi> mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Thoſe from <hi>ver.</hi> 12. to 15. were members belonging to both Societies of Paſtor and Teacher.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object. Ver.</hi> 14, 15. it is ſaid, <hi>Salute the Brethren with them:</hi> Hence the Apoſtle had no ſuch purpoſe in this place; or there were no more Societies then three in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> of Church-Societies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> The expreſſions by the Apoſtle are changed, and ſo the minde of the Apoſtle appears plainly to differ: in <hi>ver.</hi> 11. it is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>ver.</hi> 14 and 15. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which may be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of men ſerving or ſojourning with them of the diſperſed Saints. And after, <hi>ver.</hi> 16. hee joyns the whole Church together with this, <hi>Salute one another, with an holy kiſſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Ambroſ. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.11.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Narciſſus hic illo tempore Praeſbyter dicitur fuiſſe, ſicut legi in aliis codicibus, &amp; quia praeſens non erat, videris quâ cauſâ eos in Domino ſalutet ut ſanctos qui ex ejus erant domo. Hic autem Narciſſus Preſbyter officio peregrini fungebatur, exhortationibus firmans credentes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. His miniſtry conſiſted in exhortations; the Paſtor's proper duty. 2. He ſaith he had it from former writings; and therefore the more to be conſidered. 3. Where-ever he was, they are by the holy Ghoſt ſaid to be his; he was to give account to God for them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 10. thoſe of <hi>Ariſtobulus.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſte</hi> Ariſtobulus <hi>congregator intelligitur fratrum fuiſſe in Chriſto credentium, cujus factum ſic probat ut ejus diſcipulos ſuâ ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione dignos ducat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. He was the gatherer of the Brethren; which could be no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the Doctors, Miniſters properly and fitly ſo called.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:40358:17"/>2. Theſe Diſciples, he ſaith, were believers.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They are his Diſciples.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Without queſtion, as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> had that of <hi>Narciſſus</hi> left written by ſome of the Apoſtles times or immediately after; ſo he had this of <hi>Ariſtobulus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Theſe two with <hi>Aquilas</hi> ſociety make up the full Church Miniſtry.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theophilact</hi> on thoſe of <hi>Narciſſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hos nominatim non explicat, quia forte erant eorum quos ſupra meminit ſimiles:</hi> alluding to the Church in the Houſe of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quila.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adeod</hi> on <hi>ver.</hi> 5. ſaith, There were an Aſſembly of beleevers did aſſemble together at <hi>Aquila</hi>'s houſe; and that there were divers ſmall aſſemblies in one City.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Is it to be thought the famous Chuch of <hi>Rome</hi> had no other meeting places but private houſes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp. Act.</hi> 28.30. <hi>Paul</hi> taught in <hi>Rome</hi> in his own hired houſe three yeers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fox</hi> in his Martyrologie in the life of <hi>Severus, An.</hi> 224. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords this Story, to ſhew the Chriſtians of <hi>Rome</hi> had no Church builded, nor publick houſe quietly obtained; becauſe the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians having got ſome convenient place for the aſſembling of their Congregation (in which time it was doubtleſs much increaſed,) the company of Cooks or Tiplers made challenge of the place to belong to them: but the matter being brought before the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, he judged it more honeſt that the place ſhould ſerve for the worſhip of God, how ever it were, then to the dirty ſlobering of Cooks and Scullions.</p>
               <p n="12">12 <hi>El ction of Miniſters.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Cypr. lib. 2. Ep. 11. A. 240.</head>
               <p>Cognoſcant &amp; intelligant, Epiſcopo ſemel facto, &amp; Collegarum &amp; plebis teſtimonio &amp; judicio comprobato, alium conſtitui nullo modo poſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Tertull. de exhort. caſtitatis.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſque adeo niſi &amp; Laici ea obſervent per quae Praeſbyteri adle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntur, quomodo erunt Praeſbyteri qui de Laicis adleguntur?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saith he, inſomuch, unleſs the Lay-men obſerve thoſe things,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40358:17"/> for which the Presbyters are deputed; how ſhall they be Presby<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters that are deputed of the Laicks?</p>
               <p>Miniſters took the ſeveral Miniſteries on them by degrees, as <hi>Timothy</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cyp. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 2. Saith of <hi>Cornelius</hi> of <hi>Rome, Ad Sacerdotii ſublime fastidium cunctis religionis gradibus aſcendit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This appears in <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Some call him Catechiſt from his writing to the Gentiles, ſome Presbyter, ſome Biſhop, from the ſeveral places and miniſtry, as appears in his <hi>Paedag.;</hi> and <hi>Stromes</hi> he ſucceſsively took in the Church, and not <hi>per ſaltum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hieron ad Evagrium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexandriae a Marco ad Heraclem &amp; Dioniſium Epiſcopos, Praebyteri ſemper unum ex ſe electum, in excelſiori gradu colloca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Epiſcopum nominabant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ambroſe, Tim.</hi> 3.8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Poſt Epiſcopum Diaconatus ordinationem ſubjecit; quare niſi quia Epiſcopi &amp; Praesbyteri una ordinatio eſt? uterque enim ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos eſt, ſed Epiſcopus primus eſt, ut omnis Epiſcopus Presbyter ſit, non tamen omnis Presbyter Epiſcopus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>See here what the change of names is; had he held to the name Evangeliſt, it had been Truth, but is now falſe, and by Scripture reproved. <hi>Paul</hi> calls the whole miniſtry of <hi>Epheſus, Acts</hi> 20.28. Biſhops.</p>
               <p>I mention not the Election of <hi>Ambroſe, Euſeb. lib.</hi> 11. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. <hi>Auxentius</hi> being dead, he a <hi>Caterechumenus,</hi> not baptized, is choſe Biſhop againſt the minde of God, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Ordination pertained to every true Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cyp. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plane Epiſcopi non de voluntate Dei fiunt qui extra eccleſiam fiunt, ſed contra diſpoſitionem &amp; traditionem Evangeli fiunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 6, 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Poſt Philetum autem apud Antiochiam Zebenus eccleſiam ſuſcepit, quo in tempore Origenes rogatus eſt ab eccleſiis qui ſunt apud Antiochiam, ut illuc uſque pro convincendis haereticis qui inibi liberius convaluerant, perveniret. Quo cum pergeret, &amp; inter neceſſarios ageret per Palaeſtinam, Presbyter apud Caeſaream ab illius Provincae Epiſcopis ordinatur, pro hoc autem adverſum eum in humanus clivor accenditur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:40358:18"/>1. Here he is ordained at <hi>Caeſarea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. For his taking Order of Paſtorſhip or Presbyter there, and not at <hi>Antioch</hi> where he was to miniſter, of that Presbytery he kindled againſt himſelf inhumane hatred, or extream ſpite.</p>
               <p>In the following ſtory, the Biſhops of the Church of <hi>Caeſarea</hi> plead onely his ſufficiency in Preaching the Word, as if that were enough to juſtifie the act, and in that they plead this, it appears they had none but this, and that it was done againſt the Goſpel Inſtitution, and the precedent practiſe of the Churches of Chriſt; though after in the Councel of <hi>Nice</hi> this was taken violently from the Church, as I ſhall ſhew after.</p>
               <p>Again, the ſame <hi>Origen, lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>In the Church of <hi>Alexandria</hi> by <hi>Demetrius</hi> of the ſame Church, is made <hi>Catechiſt; Ei docendi magiſterium in eccleſia tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit.</hi> The ſame power the Presbytery of <hi>Alexandria</hi> had to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain him Catechiſt, they had to ordain him Paſtor and Teacher, and none had it but that Church in which it was to be exerciſed.</p>
               <p n="13">13. For conſtituting of a Church, I know but one example in ſtory extant that may give us any light herein, which was done in the beginning of the darkning of the Church way, and by him that holp to darken it.</p>
               <p>But before I proceed, it will be neceſſary to clear an Objection made by <hi>Bilſon, c.</hi> 12. <hi>perp. Church-Government;</hi> which is, that <hi>Origen, Clemens, Pautenus,</hi> were but lay men upon the words of <hi>Demetrius,</hi> ſpoken of <hi>Origen</hi> before his Ordination.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Maſter <hi>Fox</hi> thinks that <hi>Heraclas</hi> was Uſher to <hi>Origen,</hi> in keeping his School.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Igitur Origenes, injuncto ſibi à Dimetrio Epiſcopo Magisterii Officio, Grammaticam Scholam negligere coepit.</hi> Cap. 5. <hi>Origenes apud Alexandriam Doctor eccleſiae valde clarus habebatur.</hi> Lib. 6. cap. 2. <hi>Tunc adhuc Gammaticam do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centem, &amp;c.</hi> Which ſhews, he taught not School long after he taught the Goſpel, <hi>cap.</hi> 6. He had not an hours time to do it as after; and <hi>Heraclas</hi> teaching with <hi>Origen,</hi> was that way, by which he came after to become Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and governed that Church, ſucceeding <hi>Demetrius</hi> therein, <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 6.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:40358:18"/>
               <head>Euſeb. cap. <hi>11.</hi> lib. <hi>6.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Interea cum videret Origenes ſe non ſufficere ad omnia, id eſt;</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Vel in profundioribus &amp; divinioribus pertractandis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Vel in ſanctae Scripturae explanationibus diſſerendis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Vel etiam in eorum qui quotidie fidei addebantur inſtructioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, vel inſtitutionibus adimplendis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ex quibus omnibus ne reſpirare quidem ei unius ſaltem horae liberum tempus dabatur, dum ſemper ex aliis in alia vocaretur, ita ut prima luce uſque ad profundam veſperam neutiquam ceſſaret auditorium ſuum, aliis vero non recedentibus dum verbi Dei dulcedine colligati ſunt, utilius eſſe ratus eſt ſegregare incipientium turbas, &amp; uni ex diſcipulis ſuis plene jam &amp; optime inſtructo, viro atque in omnibus virtutibus ſibi probato Heracli tradere: participemque eum officii ſui ac laboris aſſumere; erat enim in Sermone diſertiſſimus &amp; in omnibus Philoſophicis eruditionibus opprimè institutus. Huic ergo tradendi prima elementa incipienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus delegat officium, ſibi vero perfectorum inſtructiones reſervat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the mean time when <hi>Origen</hi> ſaw himſelf not to be able to do all, that is;</p>
               <p n="1">1. Either for the handling of the more profound and divine things,</p>
               <p n="2">2. Or for declaring the Explanations of Scripture,</p>
               <p n="3">3. Or elſe for perfecting the Inſtructions of thoſe who daily were added to the Faith.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Here are the three operations declared of the threefold Miniſtry.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He was put on theſe things in a time of extream neceſſity.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thoſe were no things pertaining to Philoſophical School.</p>
               <p>(He proceeds) by reaſon whereof, there was not given him one hours time to breath in, whiles that always he was called from ſome to others; ſo as that from the Morning light, to the dark night, his audience never ceaſed: Some not departing.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Here it is remarkable, he taught not all confuſedly together, but went from ſome to others. That is, from thoſe he taught the profound things, to thoſe he declared the expoſitions of Scripture; and thence to thoſe whom he inſtructed in the Inſtitutions of Chriſtianity, who were daily added to the Faith.</p>
               <p n="2">2. See ſome ſtayed until others were exerciſed, even unto the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40358:19"/> dark night; each ſociety being Miniſtred unto according to his proper capacity, in its proper time and allotted place.</p>
               <p>(Again) Whiles they are gathered by the ſweetneſs of the Word of God; he thinking it more profitable to ſeparate the Aſſembly of Beginners, and to commit them to <hi>Heracles,</hi> one of his Diſciples, being a man well inſtructed and approved in all Vertues.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This was the way of the Apoſtles, taking helpers with them to the Work.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Church did ordain (that was conſtituted) Members of their ſociety of men for Miniſters, as here, <hi>Heracles,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Qui cum ab eo non ſolum in fide noſtra atque ſcientia, ſed &amp; vitae purioris inſtitutionibus ad perfectum fuiſſet inſtructus, Alexandrinae Eccleſiae praeeſſe poſt Demetrium ſubrogatus eſt.</hi> Who, ſaith he, was not inſtructed onely of him in our Faith and Knowledg, but alſo in the Inſtitutions of a purer life to perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; who was appointed after <hi>Demetrius,</hi> to govern the Church of <hi>Alexandria.</hi> Now this could not be applyed to an Uſher of an ordinary School, as by ſome.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ground of this Separation, was not altogether for his eaſe, but the peoples profit; that the Miniſtry may prove to be for the peoples greater edification.</p>
               <p n="4">4. He is approved for his vertue and knowledg, as a Miniſter of the Goſpel ought to be.</p>
               <p>(And then) he made him partaker of his office and labor.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He was partaker with him of his labor, laboring with him in the Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Of his office, to ſhew that to this work he had a call, and without it he could not undertake it, which in ſchooling was not required; and that he could make him partaker of his office by Ordination and Election of the Church.</p>
               <p>(Laſtly) What his office and his labor was, is ſet down in the laſt words. Shewing,</p>
               <p>The office delegated to him, was to teach the firſt Elements to Beginners.</p>
               <p>But reſerveth to himſelf the Inſtruction of the Perfect.</p>
               <p>This agreed neerly to the Goſpel Patern, and was alſo practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Church of <hi>Alexandria</hi> before, but on a better call; from which Inſtitution, <hi>Origen</hi> like himſelf, changeth and ſeeketh to deſtroy, as after.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:40358:19"/>
               <p>For Neoterics, it is not my purpoſe to cite any but that ye may ſee <hi>Calvine</hi> (on whoſe judgement and practice the foundation of the Presbyterie is laid,) thought otherwaies of it then thoſe which ſucceed him do, who for ought I underſtand did better diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the Eſtate of the Church under that way of Adminiſtration, then thoſe ſucceed him in it do or ſeem to do. <hi>Calvine</hi> 1. <hi>Ep. Cor.</hi> 12.28. God hath ſet in the Church, Firſt Apoſtles. Secondarily Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. Thirdly Teachers, he having ſpoken largely before and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much uncertainty or unreſolvedneſſe how the differing Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry is to be exercized in the Church, in the end concludes thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Si quis diſſentat facilè patior, neque rixas propterea excitabo: eſt enim difficile judicare de donis &amp; muneribus quibus tam dui jam orba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta fuit Eccleſia, niſi quòd veſtigia tantùm vel umbra adhuc apparent.</hi> If any (ſaith he) diſſents, I am well content, nor will I therefore ſtir up contentions; for it is hard to judge of the gifts and Offices of which the Church hath now been ſo long deprived; ſo that the ſignes only or ſhaddowes as yet appeare of them.</p>
               <p>If this be truth, then we are to inquire further for the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the true forme of Church-diſcipline then <hi>Calvine</hi> went, further then whom I think Presbytery proceeds not, though with higher and greater confidence then he did go; or were he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, I preſume would goe on his firſt diſcoveries from his owne words; nor do I ſee any thing altered in the Offices or diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of them now under the Presbyteriall forme, from that <hi>Calvine</hi> in his inſtitutions hath propoſed; but rather in that we reſt, as in the full and perfect diſcovery of the way of God; laying claime to a <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> for a conformation of it.</p>
               <p n="14">14. I come now to ſpeak a word of the Apoſtacy of Church-diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline in the Church. <hi>Euſeb.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 26. <hi>cap.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſque ad tempora</hi> Trajani <hi>virgo munda &amp; immaculata permanſit Eccleſia, corruptoribus veritatis &amp; divini verbi temeratoribus, aut nunquam omnino extantibus, aut etiam ſi qui fortè fuerant in occul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis &amp; abditis hiatibus terrae deliteſcentibus: ut verò &amp; Apoſtolorum chorus, &amp; omnis illa aetas quae a Domino ſuſceperat, vivae voces audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum de hac luce diſceſſit, tum velut in vacuam domum falſae doctrinae, impius ſe error immerſit, &amp; tanquam ubi nullus jam diutius cenſus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſor existeret nudato ut aiunt capite corripientes arma mendacii,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40358:20"/> oppugnare Apoſtolicam veritatem nituntur, ſed iſtud bellum intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecùs gerebatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nicephorus <hi>Eccleſ. hiſt. l.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. ſaith, Hereſies began about <hi>Ignatius</hi> time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. He ſaith, <hi>Simon</hi> the ſon of <hi>Mary Cleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas</hi> was ordained Biſhop: <hi>Electus ab omnibus pro eo quód eſſet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſobrinus Domini, propterea autem tunc Eccleſia virgo vocabatur, quòd nondum fuerat adulterini verbi ſubreptione corrupta, ſed</hi> Theobutes <hi>quidem quia repulſus, non meruit Epiſcopatum, ipſe caepit in initio perturbare omnia &amp; corrumpere, qui erat ex ſeptem haereſibus in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulo conſtitutis,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Here is the time of the Churches continuance in it's purity or virgin eſtate.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Here is the time and cauſe of it's Apoſtacy, <hi>Theobutus</hi> an Heretike troubling and corrupting all things, becauſe he could not be advanced to the Epiſcopacy of Jeruſalem.</p>
               <p>Yet with the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> we may ſay, that Antichriſt already wrought, for in theſe times when the Church kept not the forme of ſound words, not calling their Miniſters by their proper names, they made way for Antichriſt to riſe in a unſpeakable manner, lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle thought they that their alluſions to the legall Miniſtry, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Evangeliſt <hi>Pontifex</hi> from <hi>Aaron,</hi> the Paſtor <hi>Sacerdos</hi> from his ſons, and the Teacher <hi>Miniſter</hi> from the Levits, was the name, means and way by which Antichriſt at his inthronment ſhould take up. The ſame may be ſaid of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> if the word <hi>Epiſcopus</hi> be not adulterous, and put in for Evangeliſt, which I ſuppoſe came thus to paſſe, the whole Governments being rightly called Epiſcopacy, as ſaid of <hi>Judas,</hi> Acts 1.20. Let an other take his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; now in time the ſenior Presbyter or Government by way of eminency was called Biſhop: though <hi>à principio non fuit, Hyreneus</hi> requires in Presbyters, <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 43. <hi>ſucceſſionem Epiſcopatus.</hi> Thoſe wrote now mentioned here in this tract, <hi>Clement Rom.</hi> whoſe 1. Epiſt is ſtrangely corrupted, and divers other ſpurious writings go un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his name written long ſince, <hi>vide Scult. Anno</hi> 90. Ignatius, Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carp. Epiſt Anno 70.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dionyſius Areopag.</hi> who is queſtioned for his antiquity: the very things he is queſtioned for prove it many waies. And <hi>Sculte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> after all the objections he had made againſt his antiquity, ſaith, <hi>Quiſcunque autem</hi> Dionyſius <hi>iſte fuerit, antiquus fuerit neceſſe eſt,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40358:20"/> quòd ipſa eccleſiaſtica ordinationis forma docet, &amp;c.</hi> In his <hi>Medulla Theolog. Patrum</hi> he is ſaid to be about <hi>an.</hi> 80.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond Century corruptions began to increaſe much.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juſtinus</hi> 130.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hogeſippus</hi> 190. the 5. Books paſſe under his name, now have only the Hiſtory of the Jewes deſtruction, and nothing of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall traditions, as the right <hi>Egiſippus</hi> is ſaid by <hi>Euſebius, Nicephorus</hi> and others to have.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ireneus</hi> 170. <hi>Clem. Alex.</hi> 200.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertull. Anno.</hi> 200. ſome would 160.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertull. de proſcrip. adverſ. haeret.</hi> complaines of the Lay Peoples taking the Miniſtry on them, ſaith, <hi>Qui hodie Presbyter, cras Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe he ſhewes in his time began the corruption of the Church by a mixture of ſocieties, crying out, <hi>Pariter adeunt, pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter audiunt, pariter erant; quis Cathecumenus, quis fidelis incertum eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. See, in the beginning it was only of Catechiſts and Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, that they came in one place together, were taught together, and prayed together: what would he ſay of our Societies in which all altogether do theſe, and more alſo, receiving Sacraments alſo together?</p>
               <p n="2">2. He calls theſe Societies only then the Societies of Heretikes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The devill of this was ſuch, he obſerves it was not knowne who was a believer, who a <hi>Catecumenus:</hi> may not we ſay to him, as the Phariſees to Chriſt, <hi>in ſaying this thou reproacheſt us alſo:</hi> and no people ever were more guilty of reproach hence then we in this Kingdome are?</p>
               <p>About this time in this Kingdome was ſet up the firſt Nation<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Church in the world, the firſt Archbiſhops, and their ſuffragans in the world, if we may give any credit to our owne hiſtories, which I take to be the firſt time of preaching of the Goſpel here, or at leaſt to take a place in the Kingdome, what ever men ſay of <hi>Paul, Simon Zelotes, Joſeph of Aramathea</hi> preaching here, which they may do and not conſtitute a Church here, for the Apoſtles conſtituted not alwaies Churches where ever they came, and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Moreover, <hi>Hyreneus</hi> who lived <hi>Anno</hi> 170. in France, in his <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>adverſus Hereſ.</hi> mentions the Churches that were known
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40358:21"/> then to be in the world, but not a word of Britain, <hi>Et neque in Germaniis fundatae Eccleſiae aliter credunt aut aliter tradunt, neque in Hiſpaniis, neque in Celtis, neque in Egypto, neque in Libya, neque in Oriente, neque hae quae in medio mundo ſunt conſtitutae:</hi> Sure if in his time had been any Church in England, he ſhould have knowne of it, and would not have paſt it by in his enumeration of Churches.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Lucius,</hi> according to <hi>Harriſons</hi> Cronology, whom <hi>Holinſhed</hi> fellowes, ſaith, he began his Raigne 165. who did ſend to Rome <hi>Elvan</hi> and <hi>Meduin</hi> to <hi>Eleutherius</hi> the Biſhop to ſend Miniſters to inſtruct the people of this Land, and baptize them; who did ſend <hi>Eugatianus</hi> and <hi>Damianus,</hi> who baptized the King with all his Family and People, and therewith removed the worſhipping of Idolls and falſe gods, and taught the right means and way to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the true God, there were, ſaith he, in the bounds of Britain 28. Flamins, and three Archflamins, which were as Biſhops and Archbiſhops, or Superintendants, of the Pagan or the gentile Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, in whoſe place they being removed, were inſtituted 28. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and three Archbiſhops of the Chriſtian Religion, one of the which Archbiſhops held his Sea at London, to whom was ſubject Cornwall and all the middle part of England, to Humber, another of their Seas was at York; to whom was ſubject the North part of Britain, from Humber to the end of Scotland: the third Archfla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mins Sea was at Carleon Arwiske in Clamorganſhire, to whom was ſubject all Wales.</p>
               <p>He ſaith further this Kingdome was the firſt that openly that is indeed that did univerſally, nationally) received the Goſpel. <hi>Holinſhed Lif. Lucius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An Ancient Author I have by me ſaith, one <hi>Pagan</hi> and <hi>Elybain</hi> were ſent from Rome by <hi>Eleutherius,</hi> who baptized the people untill all the Land was baptized, going from Towne to Towne, baptizing men, more he ſaith, King <hi>Lucius</hi> made two Archbiſhops and many Biſhops.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fox</hi> out of <hi>Monumetenſis</hi> and others relates the ſame in his ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eleutherius,</hi> as <hi>Platin</hi> ſaith, lived about 171. <hi>Epistolam accepit à</hi> Lucio <hi>Rege Britanno, &amp;c. Inibi erant pontifices</hi> 25. <hi>quos Flamines vocabant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. That this is right Romiſh work, contrary to the primitive practice, none will deny I think.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:40358:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>2. This was the firſt Nation that became a Nationall Church.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It was made ſo under a Satanicall Government.</p>
               <p n="4">4. From this it went unto other Lands, and other then this was never in this Kingdome, if there had been any Church or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry hear, <hi>Lucius</hi> would never have ſent to Rome to have ſome thence to baptize him.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Ep. Clement Rom.</hi> Though corrupt yet is it Ancient: <hi>In illis verò civitatibus in quibus olim apud Ethnicos Archiflamines eorum atque primi legis Doctores erant Epiſcoporum Primates poni, vel Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tríarchas ordinavit, qui reliquorum Epiſcoporum judicia &amp; majora negotia quoties neceſſe foret in fide agitarent, &amp; ſecundum Dei vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatem ſicut conſtituerunt ſancti Apostoli, ita ut nè quis injuſtè pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riclitaretur definirent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence we may ſee the ground of Government of Archbiſhops and Biſhops, whence taken, and how and when it did begin to be, even within two years of the truth it ſelfe, and no wonder our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion continued ſo long under it, that Biſhops have pleaded the antiquity of their government.</p>
               <p>Three things confirme this ſtory.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That <hi>Gregory,</hi> who did ſend <hi>Auſtin</hi> into this Kingdome, appointed that the Sea of <hi>York</hi> ſhould have the ſame extent it had under <hi>Sampſon</hi> the firſt Archbiſhop in <hi>Lucius</hi> time, which ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the Archflamine, whoſe Juriſdiction was all Scotland, and part of England: All the Biſhops of Scotland ſince that time have fetched their conſecration thence, and ſwear Canonicall obedience to that Sea, untill the year 1466. when as <hi>George Nevil</hi> was Biſhop, in whoſe time the Scots Biſhops caſt off their Canonicall obedience on this ground, that in reſpect of the many and bloody warres, between the two Nations, the Metroplitan of <hi>York</hi> could bear no fatherly affection to his ſons of Scotland.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is ſaid that the Biſhop of <hi>Meneva,</hi> or <hi>Davids,</hi> to which that of <hi>Caerleon</hi> was removed, had ſeven ſuffragan Biſhops under him, at the coming of <hi>Austin</hi> unto the Land, who gave him a meeting to compoſe differences between them being about <hi>an.</hi> 600.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Rome</hi> was to be the Mother of Harlots, ſhe was the cauſe of this Idolatry before, as Heatheniſh Rome; for <hi>Onuphrius</hi> ſaith, in Heatheniſh Rome were three Archflamins called <hi>Dialis, Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alis, Quirinalis,</hi> He mentions only 15. more, the reſt (it's like) of them their memory periſhed with them: For <hi>Flora</hi> that Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40358:22"/> Harlot being of thoſe flamins mentioned of <hi>Onuphrius,</hi> was, as the remains prove, of her Feſtivall among us, of our 28. and came from Rome.</p>
               <p>It came hereby to be the mother of Idolatry, as it was Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Rome, the Jewes joyned Moſaycal Ceremonies and the Goſpell, the Gentiles Gentile Superſtitions and the Goſpell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.20.21.</p>
               <p>Again, in that <hi>Tertull.</hi> about the year 200. ſaith, the Britains are ſubject to the true Chriſt, but he ſaith not in the true way of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Applic. That after the 200. year of Chriſt there is no proving the true Goſpell Government from the practice of the then Churches, they being fallen into a ſtrange apoſtacy from the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell inſtitution.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As they fell ſomwhat from the practice, ſo the corruptions added of the Papiſts to them, make them abundantly the more uſeleſſe to the Church.</p>
               <p>Of the thrid Century were</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Origen An.</hi> 230. <hi>Cyprian An</hi> 240. <hi>Cornelius Rom.</hi> 250.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Origen,</hi> I ſuppoſe to be the firſt corrupted the order of Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Church, taking it not from the People and Presbytery, in which he miniſtred, but from other Biſhops of other Churches: <hi>Pro hoc autem adverſum eum inhumanus livor accenderit;</hi> and the Biſhops ordained the juſtification of their fact, plead only, <hi>Quod in praedicatione verbi ſatis clarè effloruerat. Euſeb. l.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>It appeares in that <hi>Zebenus</hi> the Biſhop was ſo much offended at it,</p>
               <p n="1">1. It was not according to the Goſpell.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It was not practiſed in the Churches.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Biſhops then did not plead, that it was proper to their function only, and not to Presbyters, as now.</p>
               <p>This will more clearly appeare, in that of <hi>Hieron. ad Evagrium. Alexandria à Marco ad Heraclam &amp; Dionyſium Epiſcopos: Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteri ſemper unum ex ſe electum in excelfiori gradu collocatum Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copum nominabant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Heraclas</hi> was <hi>Origens</hi> Scholler in whoſe time the old form ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the Church, from <hi>Mark</hi> to that day was broken; and who was more like to break it then <hi>Origen,</hi> who was of that Church, and a man (not unknown to any that have read him) of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40358:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> unſound and uncertain judgement? yet learned and witty; who did acknowledge in taking Ordination from <hi>Dimetrius</hi> at the firſt, for Catechizing, that the power of Ordination did reſide in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry true conſtituted Church: And who knoweth where God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted him to Emaſculinate himſelfe as a judgement on him for deſtroying that order by which God raiſed up ſeed in the Church, he being beſt to take the litterall, no man ſince but hath taken myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically as other things, being all forced: it may be <hi>Origen</hi> did this for ſome controverſie had between <hi>Dimetrius</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> and himſelfe, and to honor <hi>Theotiſtus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> who had ſhewed exceeding favour to him in his baniſhment at Ceſerea, who it is like were willing to take this honor to themſelves, robbing the Church of it's choiceſt Jewell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hieron.</hi> In the firſt times Biſhops differed nothing from Presbyters, and are now above them rather by the cuſtome of the Church, then by the truth of the Lords diſpoſing, and ought to rule the Church in common, which ſhewes, that the Biſhops practice in <hi>Jeroms</hi> time differed from that of the Apoſtles, and that the true primitive practice was fallen in his time.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Cornelius</hi> time <hi>Euſeb. l.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 43. at Rome numbers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one Biſhop, 46. Prieſts, 7. Deacons, 7. Subdeacons, 42. Aco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luths, 52. Exorciſts, and a numberleſſe company of Readers and Sextons: if theſe are not Popiſh corruptions, the Church in 50. years was ſtrangely altered.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> mentions in his Epiſtles the ſame names of Officers whoſe names are not written in the Goſpell-Kalender.</p>
               <p>In his time alſo there were Biſhops of Provinces, and although he held the name of Colleagues and Compresbyeters, yet the number were altered, and ſo the order among them (as appeares in many Epiſtles) is to be doubted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bilſon</hi> in his 14. cap. of Perp. Church-Government tells us, how Biſhops came to extend their Juriſdiction ſo vaſtly far about them in the Countrey.</p>
               <p>By no meanes (ſaith he) could any Countrey-Pariſhes in the Primitive Church have any Presbyters but from ſome City, and that not without the liking of the Biſhop, which forced all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Townes and Villages to matriculate and incorporate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the Church of ſome City, by whoſe Biſhop their Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters living were governed, and dying were ſupplyed.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:40358:23"/>1. It's confeſſed, they muſt incorporate, or ſhould have no Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The people and Presbyter are forced to be under his Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, or they ſhould have no Presbyter, nor will let Epiſcopall Authority go from him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It muſt be with the liking of the Biſhop, conditions are firſt agreed on between Presbyter and Biſhop, and Biſhop and People.</p>
               <p>So that whereas the Epiſcopall power ſhould reſide in every true and right conſtituted Church, the Biſhops would keep it from them, the Presbyter ſhall not be ordained, nor people be taught, if before-hand they promiſe not ſubmiſſion to the City-Biſhops Juriſdiction, and this granted by a Biſhops confeſſion, which ſhews the ſubtil courſe taken to raiſe Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>The 4. Century.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſebius Caeſarienſis,</hi> 320. <hi>Lactantius</hi> wrote to the Gentiles, but nothing of the Church-Diſcipline at all.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Athanaſius</hi> 370.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hylarius</hi> 370.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bazilius,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> 370.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hieronimus,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ambroſius,</hi> 370.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Augustinus,</hi> 370.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The Church was to go into the wilderneſſe, and be hid to the world in the Yeare 406.</p>
               <p>It was to remain hid 1260. yeers.</p>
               <p>That the number of Antichriſt may be 1666.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Euſebius,</hi> l. 5. cap. 9. ſaith of the time of <hi>Pantenus,</hi> about 210.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Erant enim adhuc in illis Temporibus &amp; Evangeliſtae nonnulli, qui ad imitationem ſanctorum Apoſtolorum in diverſis orbis partibus oberrantes, per gratiam Dei &amp; animi ſui virtutem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. It is to cleare theſe of theſe times could not be extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily called, nor I think were they extraordinarily gifted; untill theſe times the Church kept it's true forme, and it's like the ſenior Presbyter was of many called the Evangeliſt, however altered in their writings.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It ſeemes that after theſe times the name and the office of Evangeliſt ceaſed in the Church.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In the Councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> his office was deſtroyed, and an Antichriſtian Officer put in his place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Canon</hi> 10. <hi>Et nè in una civitate ſunt duo Epiſcopi;</hi> which proves, before this Canon or Councell there were in ſome Cities two
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40358:23"/> Biſhops, there being in them two compleat Churches. A high ſtep, made to help Antichriſt into his throne.</p>
               <p>Councell of Antioch took downe the Country Evangeliſt or Biſhop; as Nice the City.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conceditur Chorepiſcopis, ut ordinent Lectores, Subdiaconos, &amp; Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orcistas, de ſuperioribus ordinibus decernitur, ut nec Presbyterium nec diaconum ordinare audeant praeter civitatis Epiſcopum, cui ipſe cum poſſeſſione ſubjectus eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Had not Country Biſhops ordained all degrees of orders in the Church, they by a Councell would not have granted the leſſer, and have denied the greater.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whereas he may do it by leave of the City Biſhop, though not without, ſhewes the act was lawfull according to God, or how could it be done by the allowance of men.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If it were lawfull according to God, then the tyranny of Antichriſt was great in theſe times.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zozomen l.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 19.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Etenim per Scithiam cum civitates multae unum duntaxat, hae omnes Epiſcopum habent, apud alias vero Nationes reperias ubi in pagis E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopi ordinantur, ſicut apud Arabes; Cyprios, apud Novatianos, Montaniſtas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. This is more then is written of any after his time, this was quickly altered when Antichriſt came to his throne in the world.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Theſe that held the Church forme, went under the name of Novatians, Montaniſts, Sectaries.</p>
               <p>The ground they had to diſtinquiſh the Country from the City Biſhop, was that the Country Biſhop was reſembled in the 70. the City Biſhop in the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>But as it is well obſerved of Mr. <hi>Rutherford, p.</hi> 476. of a Presby. Church at Antioch.</p>
               <p>Look what frame of Churches the Apoſtles did inſtitute in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that ſame they behoved to inſtitute in villages alſo, for places cannot change the inſtitution of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And before p. 470. on Acts. 8.5.6. When <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> came to Samaria, to help <hi>Philip,</hi> it cannot be that they all went to one houſe, and to one ſingle aſſembly to preach the Word.</p>
               <p>And Page before 460. on 1. Cor. 14.15. I baptized none but <hi>Cryſpus</hi> and <hi>Gaius,</hi> &amp;c. If many were baptized, other Paſtors not <hi>Paul</hi> baptized them, and ſo they were baptized in other Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40358:24"/> then in thoſe in which <hi>Paul</hi> baptized, Acts. 18.8. Many Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians were baptized.</p>
               <p>I paſſe by theſe and come to my task, though theſe are the truths I intend.</p>
               <p>Chryſoſt. on Eph. 4.11. <hi>Tertio Evangeliſtas non circumeuntes, ſed Evangelizantes; ut erant</hi> Priſcilla <hi>&amp;</hi> Acyla, <hi>Paſtores &amp; Doctores quibus viz. univerſus populus concreditus erat; Quid ergo juniores erant Paſtores ac Doctores? admodum erant enim circumeuntibus, &amp; Evangelizantibus inferiores, qui habitando quieti circa unum dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at locum occupabantur; ut</hi> Timotheus <hi>ac</hi> Titus, <hi>verùm alias ex hoc loco ſubjectio &amp; praelatura colligi non poteſt;</hi> and after, <hi>Nè quid huic expoſitionis meae contradicas, poteſt fieri, ut Evangeliſtas eos hic intelligta, qui Evangelium conſcripſerunt.</hi> If <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> were thus ignorant of the Office of Evangeliſts, no wonder if we are; one while he is for walking Evangeliſts, then for thoſe abide in one place; and to theſe he adheres, or elſe prelature cannot be proved thence; and then he comes to thoſe wrote the Goſpells, how can it be thought poſſible ſo great a darkneſſe ſhould come on the world in ſo ſhort a time, on thoſe who had the learning of the age?</p>
               <p>And it is like the Ancient copies of the primitive Writers, were either loſt, hid, or corrupted before his time, making way for the departure of the Church, now about to take its leave of the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bazil.</hi> in an Epiſtle to <hi>Ambroſe</hi> cals on him <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Montacu</hi> of Tythes, underſtands this complaint of his to be only about the dividing of Cappadocia into two Metropolitans; which had been one at Caeſarea.</p>
               <p n="1">1. I conceive <hi>Bazil</hi> underſtands the firſt tract of the Fathers, in which only was a reformation that was right, and not that went immediately before.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Nor could that be underſtood well, for the old marks for it were not 200. years, before that there were no provinciall Biſhops in all the world.</p>
               <p>And after, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. which ſhewes, he ſought this in ſome ſpirituall way, and for a ſpirituall end, quite contrary to that objected before.</p>
               <p>And in his Epiſtle to <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> I conceive he implieth the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40358:24"/> ſame, when he calls on him to joyne with him in reſtoring the Church <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in which he alludes to the alluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>John the Baptist,</hi> to the Goſpell Government, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.12. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to me it ſeems, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> more fully manifeſts the Goſpell truth, and then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> more full, to which no government then did ſo fitly agree, as the Goſpell government.</p>
               <p>Applic. Seeing he calls on <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and <hi>Ambroſe</hi> to reforme by the firſt times, it proves there is no true reformation to be made of the Church by the practice of the then times, leaſt we would ſeek to prove one corruption by another.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the true Church-diſcipline was neare gone from the world, or going, as he inſtanceth, onely <hi>Antioch,</hi> whoſe practice he commends, which doubtleſſe was deficient in many things in thoſe times.</p>
               <p>Ambroſe Eph. 4. <hi>Coepit alio ordine &amp; providentiâ gubernari Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia;</hi> and points out the time to be <hi>ubi omnia loca circumplexa eſt Eccleſia,</hi> it was after doubtleſſe the 200. yeare.</p>
               <p>O <hi>Ambroſe!</hi> did they think of the curſe denounced of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle againſt men or Angells, ſhould attempt this, or had they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine revelations to do it, or Apoſtolicall Authority delegated, that they dare to do ſuch a thing!</p>
               <p>After he gives us the reaſon; <hi>Scripta Apoſtoli ideo non per om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia conveniunt ordinationi quae nunc in Eccleſia est, quia hac inter pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mordia ſunt conſcripta.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As if the government written in the Goſpell, and exerciſed by the Apoſtles, was onely for the Apoſtles time, or Church-Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and would not ſerve all eſtates thereof, in which we ſee the plea now uſed is an old one.</p>
               <p>An inſtance he gives of this in <hi>Timothy,</hi> made a Presbyter by <hi>Paul,</hi> and called a Biſhop, <hi>ut recedente eo, ſequens ei ſuccederet,</hi> that is, the Evangeliſt dying, the ſenior Presbyter, the Paſtor ſucceeded him, he being next in place and office.</p>
               <p>The reaſon of this change is this: <hi>Sed quia coeperunt ſequentes Preſbyteri indigni inveniri ad primatos tenendos, mutata eſt ratio pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiciente conſilio, ut non ordo, ſed meritum crearet Epiſcopum multo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum judicio conſtitutum, nè indignus temerè uſurparet et eſſet multis ſcandalum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. If any ſuch there had been, the Lord had provided a remedy
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40358:25"/> againſt it, by giving the Church a power among themſelves to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it, which here the Biſhops, to the deſtruction of that privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge uſurp to themſelves.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is done by a Councell, that it may have the more fair pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and that hereby unworthy men may not come <hi>ad primatos tenendos.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the ſenior Presbyter ſucceeded the Evangeliſt, if fit, is il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrated in that of <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Eleazer</hi> his eldeſt ſon, <hi>Numb.</hi> 20.25, 26.</p>
               <p>But ſee what the Biſhops did with this uſurped authority, when wreſted from the Church quickly after.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sozom. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. tells a ſtory of a Biſhop choſen by Biſhops, for Conſtantinople.</p>
               <p>He was choſen by <hi>Diodorus</hi> meanes, and commended to the Councell, his name was <hi>Nectarius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That which they choſe him for is, becauſe he had a white head, a ſacerdotall Countenance, and the like; this fitted him <hi>ad prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos tenendos.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. He was not a man baptized; it is ſaid <hi>Diodorus</hi> ſeeing him ſo grave a man, thought he had been baptized.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He is exhorted to give him to reading, which ſhewes, he had little abilities in him to teach.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Ap. Could this be ſaid of a ſenior Presbyter, he muſt be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter qualified then ſo.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let man never give leave to man to change the everlaſting Ordinances of God for never ſo faire pretences, for the fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God is wiſer then men.</p>
               <p>In the ſame manner <hi>Ambroſe</hi> was elected before baptized, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Word.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ambroſe</hi> on the ſame 4. <hi>Eph.</hi> ſaith of the Teachers, <hi>Doctores ſunt hi qui lectionibus imbuendi infantes ſolebant imbuere, ſicut mos Iudaeorum eſt quorum traditio ad nos tranſitum fecit, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> per negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentiam obſolevit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He ſheweth, though the cuſtome were taken from the Jewes, yet it belonged to the Gentiles, to have it exerciſed in their Churches alſo.</p>
               <p>The Doctor being to initiate their children in grace, as the Jewiſh theirs in nature, which through negligence is out of uſe, of whoſe Ordination he thus writes, <hi>Prophetia est qua eligitur qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi Doctor futurus idoneus, manus verò impoſitiones verba ſunt myſtica
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40358:25"/> quibus confirmatur ad opus electus auctoritatem teste conſcientia ſua ut audeat vice Domini ſacrificium Deo offerre,</hi> 1 <hi>Timoth.</hi> 4.14.</p>
               <p>1 <hi>Timoth.</hi> 5. <hi>Apud omnes uti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> gentes honorabilis est ſenectus, unde Synagoga &amp; poſtea Eccleſia, ſeniores habuit, quorum ſine Conſilio nihil agebatur in Eccleſia, quòd qua negligentia obſoluerit neſcio, niſi fortè Doctorum deſidiâ aut magis ſuperbiâ dum ſoli volunt aliquid videri.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereby <hi>Seniores</hi> M. <hi>B lſon</hi> will not admit the helping Governor, or ruling Elder to be underſtood, but that advice which Biſhops uſed to take of Presbyters, was now not taken in Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He alludes in this place, as I ſuppoſe, to that 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.8, 9, 10. where with the Prieſts and Levites there are of the heads of the people <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Here it ſeems to me Senior is oppoſed to Doctor, I ſuppoſe if he had intended as it is objected, he would have ſet downe <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcoporum</hi> rather then <hi>Doctorum,</hi> which comprehends the whole Miniſterie.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is cleare the Church-ruling Elder in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. was ceaſed before his time, and practiſed as I think by the Biſhops and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſt.</hi> cited by <hi>Calvin</hi> on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. ſaith thus, which confirms it; <hi>In libro de opere Monachorum ubi ſuas occupationes commemorat, hanc ſibi de multis vel moleſtiſſimam eſſe aſſerit, quòd ſecularibus ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiis partem diei impendere cogatur, ſe tamen patienter ferre, quia ejuſmodi neceſſitatem ſibi Apoſtolus injungat ex hoc loco, &amp; quadam Epiſtola apparet, ſolitos certis horis ſedere Epiſcopos ad lites-dirimendas, quaſi eos hic deſignet Apoſtolos, ut autem res in deterius ſemper labun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ex illo errore deinde manabit Juriſdictio, quam ſibi in cauſis pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuniariis Epiſcoporum officiales uſurpant, in illo autiquo more duo ſunt reprehenſione digna, quod Epiſcopi alienis à ſuo officio negotiis implicabantur, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. This of judging in civill cauſes, was the office of the helping Governour, which the Biſhops in and after <hi>Ambroſe</hi> time exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted themſelves.</p>
               <p n="2">2. M. <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith, this was a buſineſſe belonged not to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; he calls it in them <hi>malum tolerabile,</hi> yet ſee how <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, it was deſigned them by Apoſtles.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In that he ſaith, <hi>in alienis negotiis,</hi> ſhewes it was a buſineſſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40358:26"/> pertained to ſome, and it muſt be a Church-Officer, though not them which was the Ruling Elder.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hieron.</hi> on <hi>Ep. Tit. cap.</hi> 1. ſhewes the reaſon why it was decreed in the whole world, that all the care of the Church ſhould pertain to one, and that was from the primary diſſentions of Presbyters; which was, that whereas when the three Presbyters governed the Church together, they could not agree among themſelves: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they would have the Government onely to be in one, and not in three any more. A faire excuſe it was, even for the peace of the Church.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If they walked by the Rule, how could they diſagree?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Tyranny of Antichriſt could never get up by three, but by one in giving government to one in the Church, was much of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt revealed, and made way for all.</p>
               <p>Applic. 1. Mixt ſocieties are ſet up, and Nationall Churches con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, Ordination is taken from the Church, and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church by its owne Presbyters is deſtroyed, Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts rooted up, and Teachers office caſt down, and the helping Ruler is taken away: whereas were two Biſhops in a City, now one rules a whole Province; theſe proceed to Patriarks, which preceded the Pope, all this is left upon Record, &amp; that the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church was not in <hi>Ambroſe</hi> time ſuch as in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I deſire thoſe read, and intend to write againſt what is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained to cleare,</p>
               <p n="1">1. How.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When theſe things thus ſaid to be altered, came to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether that a government be right that hath not all, and no more then all that the Apoſtles practiſed and left to be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Church.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether the <hi>Conventicula quae constituta ſunt &amp; Rectores &amp; caetera Officia in Eccleſia ordinata,</hi> ſpoke of <hi>Ambroſe, Eph.</hi> 4. have not reſpect to ſingle Congregations the ſame now amongſt us, in oppoſition to Goſpell Churches, conſiſting of ſeverall ſocieties ſet up uſually in Cities, if not what they were then?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Whether his <hi>Capit alio ordine &amp; prudentia gubernari Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> ſignifie not that then one Miniſter came to do all, and all parts of Miniſtery were done in the <hi>Conventiculis,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er have been
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40358:26"/> ſince, and where this uſed by us be not <hi>ab alio ordine &amp; prudentia quam eo quod à Deo eſt in Evangelio,</hi> if not, in what the conſtitution of our Churches do differ from theirs here mentioned.</p>
               <p>That I may bring you to the Pope, in whoſe manifeſtation the Goſpell-Government was fully hid; In the time of <hi>Theodo.</hi> the younger, <hi>Anno,</hi> 423. which is but 17. yeares after the time of the Churches obſcuring, the higheſt of Antichriſt was manifeſted in a manner in the publike Charter, granted Bononia for the making of an Univerſity.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="charter">
                  <body>
                     <p>WE <hi>Theodoſius</hi> by the grace of God, Emperor of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, ever <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> moved with the commodiouſneſſe and fertility of the place, having 25. moneths taken found and deliberate advice therein, ſitting in our ſeat of Majeſty, a generall councell of Chriſtians being aſſembled in the preſence of <hi>Celeſtine</hi> high Biſhop of Rome, 12. Cardinals, Arch-biſhops and Biſhops innumerable, and ſundry other Dukes and Princes of divers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and callings, <hi>Baldwine</hi> Earle of Flanders, and <hi>Gaulter</hi> Earle Poictiers, Embaſſadors, the one repreſenting the perſon of the King of France, the other of the King of England, the whole Colledge of an 100. ſenators ſitting, do by this inviolable act, &amp;c.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Given at Rome in the Capitoll.
<date>Anno 423. May. 11.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This made the Pope truly Antichriſt, when he counterfeited Chriſts Ordinance, by ſetting up that in his falſe Church in a falſe way, which Chriſt ſet up in the true; his 12. to Chriſts 12. which are above Archbiſhops and Biſhops, Dukes and Princes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clem. recognit. l.</hi> 3. though a counterfeit, yet is it ancient. <hi>Haec au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem &amp; his ſimilia cum dixiſſet</hi> Petrus, <hi>manibus ſuperpoſitis</hi> Zacheo, <hi>oravit ut inculpabiliter Epiſcopatus ſui ſervaret officium: poſt haec</hi> 12. <hi>Presbyteros ordinavit, &amp; diaconos</hi> 4. Theſe are ſaid to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to ſerve at Ceſarea to juſtifie the Roman practice, and their 12. Cardinals, though not a word in Scripture witneſſe any ſuch thing at all.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:40358:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Having briefly ſpoken of the fall, I ſhall propoſe one Propheticall Scripture for the riſe of the fallen Churches, Gentiles as well as Jewes, together now ſhortly to be within 18. years in moſt of the world.</p>
               <p>Ezek. 16.55. When thy Siſter Sodome and her daughters ſhall returne to their former eſtate, and Samaria and her daughters ſhall returne to their former eſtates, then thou and thy daughters ſhall returne to your former eſtate.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To underſtand this, note that in Scripture, the firſt Churches are called Mother Churches, thoſe that ſucceed them, and are conſtituted according to them, and receive miniſtry and means mediately from them, are not unfitly called Daughter Churches, whether they are true or falſe, and in this it well agrees, <hi>ſuch as the mother ſuch as the daughter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. In this ſence it cannot be ſaid of literall Sodome, ſhe was no Church, ſhe had no daughters, but in Rev. 11.8. Rome myſtically is ſaid to be called Sodome; and ſurely no where, if not here in all the Book of God, ſhe is the mother of Harlots, that is of idolatrous Churches, and ſocieties: and in 7. Seſſ. Councell of Trent, <hi>can.</hi> 3. <hi>De Baptiſmo,</hi> ſhe is called <hi>Mater omnium Eccleſiarum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. All the Churches, before An 200. conſtituted according to the Apoſtles, were Jeruſalem and after to the 400 year.</p>
               <p n="2">2. All the Idolatrous falſe Churches, ſet up after Antichriſt of Rome ſince the year 46. are Romes daughters.</p>
               <p n="3">3. All the Societies ſeparated from Rome within this 150. years, being not according to the Goſpell frame, or patterne, are Samarias daughters.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Their Prieſt was brought from Aſſyria, or Babell, as was <hi>Martine Luther</hi> from the Monaſtery.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They made Gods of their owne, every Nation as they pleaſe, 2. Kings 17.27.29.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Ver. 41. Theſe Nations feared the Lord, and ſerved the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Images, both their children and childrens children, as did their fathers.</p>
               <p>The Application I leave to the Reader.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:40358:27"/>1. It is obſervable, <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> is firſt, <hi>Sodom</hi> next, <hi>Samaria</hi> laſt, in Scripture and in time; yet <hi>ver.</hi> 46. <hi>Samaria</hi> is called the elder ſiſter, and <hi>Sodom</hi> the younger; yet firſt in time and Scripture, God in this ſhewing the <hi>Samaritan</hi> eſtate had more of the truth then <hi>Sodoms</hi> eſtate, and ſo may be ſaid to be elder, and hath honour gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven her of God in it, and <hi>Sodom</hi> diſhonour.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Ieruſalems, Sodoms, Samarias</hi> daughters, ſhall be brought all again to their former eſtate, that is the primitive goſpel-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In the bringing <hi>Sodoms</hi> and <hi>Samarias,</hi> God will bring again <hi>Ieruſalems</hi> Captives, the Iewes in the midſt of them, their call pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and time intimated.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Ver.</hi> 61. Thou ſhalt receive thy ſiſter, thy elder and thy younger; here <hi>Samaria</hi> is ſpoke of firſt, who firſt ſhall have the goſpel government ſet up in her, and ſhall be acknowledged by the goſpel to be ſo, and then God ſhewes how, in ſaying he will give them to <hi>Ierualem</hi> for daughters, who before were <hi>Sodoms</hi> and <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rias, Rev.</hi> 20.6. this is the firſt reſurrection of Churches</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> When ſhall this bee?</p>
               <p n="1">1. When <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> hath born her lewdneſſe, <hi>ver.</hi> 5.8.</p>
               <p n="2">2. After <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> hath had all her daughters, and <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> all her daughters, and <hi>Samaria</hi> or the Church departed from <hi>Rome</hi> had her daughters.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They and their daughters are ſaid to dye, as it were, as the true Churches were aboliſhed by Anti-chriſt, Anti-chriſt by <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria;</hi> God now by giving the truth, aboliſheth Epiſcopacy and Presbytery the daughters of <hi>Samaria,</hi> and giving the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the goſpel-government, firſt to <hi>Samaria</hi> which I think will be ſeen in <hi>England;</hi> God is ſaid to bring <hi>Samarias</hi> daughters, and then after will <hi>Romes</hi> daughters, <hi>France, Spaine, &amp;c.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whoſe returne the Iewes ſhall be called, and returne alſo, and the new <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſhall receive them for daughters. So that I ſuppoſe the true goſpel-government will be ſet up, and ſpread into farther parts, Dominions and Countreys, then ever the Apoſtles ſpread it, and continue much longer in time and purity in the world.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Sodom and Samaria</hi> ſhall lay down in a ſhort time their corruptions, abominations, and falſe government, taking up the way of God.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:40358:28"/>5. This cannot be underſtood of the laſt day of Iudgement, that after that reſurrection the ſpirituall harlot <hi>Sodom</hi> or <hi>Samaria</hi> ſhall be daughters, that is be conſtituted Churches according to the goſpel pattern.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Nor of <hi>Sodom</hi> burnt by fire, in <hi>Gen.</hi> 20. for they ſhall never hereafter be given to be daughters to <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. This Scripture held by ſome to make againſt the call of the Iews, rightly underſtood, makes a ſtrong and undeniable proof of it as any whatſoever.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Scripture following, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.20. compared with <hi>Luke</hi> 19.17. the firſt which is he in <hi>Matthew</hi> had the five Talents, is promiſed to bee in <hi>Luke</hi> made Ruler of ten Cities, which ſeemes to me to ſhew that there ſhall be abundance more of Churches under the new <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to be, then under that that was; the Gentiles ſhall bring their glory, riches, that is, wiſedom, learning, knowledge, their all unto it. In which is ſhewn how the Miniſtry ſhall bee taken from the ſingle Miniſtry, and given to the true Church Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination, after which, before the end, may be Apoſtacy to a twofold Miniſtry, but never to a ſingle Miniſtry more.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Math,</hi> 25.14, 15, <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In theſe words of <hi>Matthew,</hi> are to bee conſidered two generall things. 1. That which is the Parabolicall ſence of the Scripture. 2. That which is the Myſticall or the Prophetick ſence. In the firſt we are to conſider what this Parable is alledged for by the Lord, and that is to ſet out the Kingdom of Heaven by, not in the inward operations of it on the Soule, but the outward adminiſtrations of it in the Miniſtry of the word, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Yee have the way the Lord takes in the diſpoſing the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, called the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, hee did it by a call, the way by which he ordained his Diſciples at the firſt, and ſtill doth by an ordinary call of his meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and without which none are to undertake the Miniſtry.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Thoſe that are called, ate called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> his own ſervants: in which is ſignified the ſeparating of the Miniſters of the goſpel from all other imployments, and the deſtinating of them unto this only, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.4. without which the Miniſtry cannot be diſcharged.</p>
               <p n="3">3. After their Call and Separation, then he comes to intruſt them with the diſpenſations of the goſpel, rightly called his goods, in which Sathan nor the world have not the leaſt property, which
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40358:28"/> are left to the Miniſters only, not the people, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1.2.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In the number of his ſervants which are three, they have the number of the Miniſters ordained by Chriſt, for the right govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church in this world untill the end.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Yee have the diſpoſing of theſe goods of Chriſt remarkably ſet down, the manner how, and that is not all to any one, but one hath one, another two, the third five Talents.</p>
               <p n="6">6. He that had his one, had his Call from Chriſt, his Ordination from Chriſt, his intruſtment, his Talent from Chriſt, that is <hi>Jure Divino</hi> as well as he that had five.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Theſe are delivered to each according to his ability:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Signifying, that one of the Church Miniſters hath more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him then an other.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He that had five, had as much as his ability could enable him to exerciſe, he could not exerciſe the two the ſecond had, or that one more then his own five which the third had:</p>
               <p n="3">3. Which ſhewes, it was not the minde of Chriſt, nor is it in the power of man to exerciſe the whole Miniſtry, which by the Lords Inſtitution is to be done by three.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> This is a novelty and a new found Expoſition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſp.</hi> If it be the truth, receive it though; but <hi>Clemen. Alex. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Stro.</hi> underſtands hereby the Teachers of the Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. An uncertaine Author on <hi>Mathew</hi> tranſlated by <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> and bound up with the third <hi>Tom.</hi> of <hi>Chryſoſtome<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> applyeth theſe to the Miniſtry; firſt, the five Talents to the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> which he makes to be Government, Preaching, Baptiſm, offering Sacrifice, and Prayer for the People.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The two Talents to the Deacon, which he makes his godly life and faithfull Miniſtry in his Deaconſhip.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The one Talent he underſtands to be the Peoples knowledge.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Miniſtry of the Goſpel was fallen in <hi>Chyſoſtomes</hi> times, in moſt places of the world; hence it is no wonder if it be applyed to the Miniſtry; the application holdeth not correſpondency with the Text.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If one be to be applyed to the Miniſtry, then all are; there is no difference in call, in appointment to the Miniſtry, in the Steward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, in the nature of the goods that the one had or the other, but in the quantity only.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If this be ſaid of the people and Miniſters, then all Miniſteriall
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40358:29"/> differences are deſtroyed betwixt People and Miniſters hereby.</p>
               <p>Many have given their judgement what theſe Talents are ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall wayes, as <hi>Salmeron</hi> in <hi>Parabolis,</hi> but I paſſe that, and come to the myſticall ſence or prophetick.</p>
               <p n="1">1. God predicts by the unprofitableneſſe of the man only which had but one Talent, which indeed is the firſt Miniſtry called the Doctor, the miſery of the Church under a ſingle Miniſtry, in the time of Antichriſt, whoſe work it was to deſtroy the true Goſpel-Miniſtry of three, and ſet up his <hi>Bable</hi> Miniſtry of one ſingly in the World inſtead thereof.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God predicts he ſhould have but one Talent that ſhould bee truly gold, which is the Word; the reſt under that Miniſtry, ſhould be corrupt ſpurious falſe and fained things, indeed ſcroffe and droſſe to be burned.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Vnder this one unfaithfull Miniſtry ſhould be a hiding of that Talent it had, which ſignifieth a hiding or ſhutting up of the Scriptures in an unkwon tongue.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The converting the Goſpel-Government contained in the Word, which was from heaven and heavenly, into an earthly conſtitution tending only to wordly glory and greatneſſe, the one being of God, the other of man, the one the pattern of heavenly things, the other of earthly things.</p>
               <p>The doome of God written of him, verſ. 29. cleares the truth of the intended myſtery, from him that hath not, ſhall be taken that which he hath.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This cannot be underſtood of any but of a Miniſter, nor be verified in a particular perſon, but muſt be done in a publick ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall generall ſence of Scripture; you may apply it to <hi>Judas</hi> in ſome kinde, who was the lively repreſentative of Antichriſt: But 1. he without all queſtion had more then one Talent: 2. This here doth mainly intend the ordinary Church-Miniſtry and not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Scripture ſaith he hath the goods of his Lord, and againe he is ſaid not to have them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Signifying that he ſhould have nominally, formally, and in ſhew thoſe things the true Church of God hath.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That he hath them not really and indeed according to the Lords Inſtitution, the Word indeed it hath, and the people may be ſaid not to have it while they have it, having it in an unknown tongue.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:40358:29"/>3. God will take away that which he ſeemeth to have:</p>
               <p n="1">1. This we ſee partly done in the diſcovery the World hath in part already made of her Idolatrous Worſhip.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the Saints, condemning her Church, Church-Miniſtry and Ordinances, to be Anti-chriſtian, Superſtitious, Heatheniſh and ungodly.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The full taking away, will be when God ſhall erect a true faithfull Miniſtry and pure Ordinances among his Saints in the place of that Idol worſhip, as in verſ. 28.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Appl.</hi> 1. Theſe all meet in Antichriſt as lines of a circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in its Center, and ſo in him as in none but him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Antichriſt, is he the Goſpel Propheſies aime at, that ſhould diſturb, counterfeit, and oppoſe the truth of the Lord, under whom the Church changes ſhould be.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Antichriſt, is he from whom the Talent ſhall be taken, who is indeed <hi>tho unprofitable ſervant</hi> to his Lord in the Miniſtry, hee being to be deſtroyed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. How in a generall Scripture-ſence, theſe can be underſtood of any, but Anti-chriſt I know not (but ſhould gladly be enformed) he is to be a called Miniſter, and intruſted with the Goſpel which the firſt Biſhops were by the Lords Inſtitution; he proves unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, hides the Word, turnes the Diſcipline of it to earthly advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that hiding the Goſpel ends muſt have a fall and be ruin'd, his Miniſtry taken from him, after which the Church is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Myſtery, in the verſ. 28. where the Talent is taken from him, and given to him that hath tenne Talents.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In which is ſhewed Antichriſts Miniſtry ſhall be deſtroyed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In that it is given to the firſt, it ſhewes the reſtauration of the Goſpel-Miniſtry and Government in the Church againe to bee as in the beginning.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That God will bleſſe by degrees in the uſe of meanes, that Miniſtry to whom the one Talent ſhall be given, abundantly, from five to tenne, which ſhewes it will be extraordinary, but not by an extraordinary way, as verſ. 16.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is given to the firſt Miniſtry which is the Evangeliſt, the act of Ordination being Primarily in him, by whom with others the Church ſhould come to be re-eſtated, and to him had two which was the Paſtors.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:40358:30"/>5. The taking away of the one, and the giving of the one Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, ſignifies that Authoritatively by ſome one that has power to doe it, this act ſhall be done in the Church before the burnings of Anti-chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 1. Here he that had five, hath tenne, which is more then all the Miniſtry had, which were but eight in all; and therefore one man may exerciſe all.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Shewes the abundance of knowledge the Miniſters of the Goſpel that ſhall be, ſhall be bleſſed with, and how happy the world ſhall be in them, or in particular him that is deſigned for the Churches reſtauration.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What is ſignified by the words <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, other five Talents; firſt, they are other indeed, but not in kinde as the three other Talents are which doe differ in kinde from his five, but the ſame five Talents or gifts are encreaſed in him, in the uſe of them more then they were double.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Though he had tenne, the other that had two, had foure, and the unprofitable ſervant had his one, ſo that he that had the tenne, did not like <hi>Pharohs</hi> cattell, one eat up the other.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The one's being given to him that had the ten, was but that he that had the ten as the Apoſtles by their extraordinary Call, did before come to ſet up by Gods approbation, the Ordinances in the Church of Chriſt as they were firſt inſtituted in the Word, which when once done, he was to leave it to them to exerciſe as the Apoſtles had done before him, and only exerciſe his owne part ordinarily in the Church.</p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>Having ſpoken of the Church-Miniſtry, we now come to ſpeak of the Church-Elder, or helping Ruler.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>MEn to pleaſe the Magiſtrate have demoliſhed this Officer out of the Church, and ſet up a counterfeit in his place, for whom I dare boldly affirm there is no one word of Inſtitution in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel to be found, to doe that he is appointed to doe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The true helping Governour:</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Is indeed a Lay-Elder.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His Inſtitution is without laying on of hands, <hi>Bilſon. cap.</hi> 11. <hi>perp. Church-Government;</hi> if they had laying on of hands, they had not been Lay-Elder.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:40358:30"/>3. The goſpel hath inſtituted no Church-lay Officer, but that of 1 Cor, 6.1.6. who was only ſet up to compoſe differences in the Church in civill affaires.</p>
               <p n="4">4. There is no inſtitution for any ſuch Officer in the Church, as the Lay-Elders under Presbytery are aſſigned unto: ſo they cannot but be an Anti-Chriſtian Office acting by a Anti-Chriſtian power, unleſſe we ſay there are to be Officers and Offices in the Church that are not of goſpel inſtitution. As for that brought to prove them out of 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.9.10. it is of no validity; Chriſt ſaith, <hi>No man putteth an old piece, no not a piece to a new Garment;</hi> therefore that is not Chriſts mind that they whatever their Office was, ſhould be to rule under the goſpel, though I think their Office was far differing from Lay-Elders now.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Office of the Elder was not about Eccleſiaſticall things, but 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an ordinary buſineſſe, <hi>ver.</hi> 1. and then <hi>ver.</hi> 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the leſſer things, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, things of this life or live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood; and to this, <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.19.11. <hi>Amariah</hi> is for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Lord, and <hi>Zebadiah</hi> in the matters of the King, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. proves it clearely.</p>
               <p>The word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifieth the Churches inſtituting ſome, and in an autoritative way among themſelves for determining differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces amongſt them, occaſioned about things aboveſaid, as in <hi>ver.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>Queſtion will be whether the governour ſet up by the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> were <hi>Iure divino.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Governours <hi>Rom</hi> 12.8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. are ſaid to be ſet up of God in the Church; the ſame is meant doubtleſſe, 1 <hi>Tim. chap.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 17. Inſtitution for an other Governour then this in this 6 to the <hi>Corinthians;</hi> I prove all thoſe hold the contrary, to ſhew, 1. The grounds to be obſerved by the Church in ordaining Lay-Elders, are laid downe by the Apoſtle in this Chapter as fully as for the ordaining any other Officer in the Church: Firſt hee muſt be qualified with wiſedome, a wiſe man: Secondly a Church-member: Thirdly a member of their owne Church, a wiſe man amongſt them; which proves it to be a proper office pertaining to the well governing of every Church: Fourthly they are to bee ſet up to judge by the Churches authority. Fifthly the Apoſtle doth approve the practiſe by arguments drawn <hi>à majore ad minùs;</hi> they are juſt, therefore fit to judge, and more fit then thoſe are unjuſt, before whom they brought their Cauſes to tryall, they ſhall judge
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40358:31"/> the World and Angels, how much more the things of this life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> If theſe are <hi>Iure divino,</hi> then whether are they to continue in the Church or not, they being ſet down in Scripture to be ſet up in the Primitive Church?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſponſ.</hi> Maſter <hi>Bilſon</hi> Chap. 10. <hi>Perpet. Church Government,</hi> ſaith, they had no authority, neceſſity, nor perpetuity; and after in Chriſtian Common-Wealths theſe Iudges muſt ceaſe, becauſe there is no cauſe of declinining the Tribunall of Chriſtian Magiſtrates.</p>
               <p>Yet he himſelfe confeſſeth theſe to be Governours and Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratours of their brethrens quarrels and contentions; others he finds not in the Apoſtolick writings, but ſuch as withall were watchmen and ſeeders, <hi>Chap. ibid. pag.</hi> 142. who then if not theſe were the helping Governours?</p>
               <p n="1">1. He cals them Governours, and yet ſaith rhey had no autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. God requires obedience to thoſe that rule well.</p>
               <p n="2">2 They were ſet up or appointed by the whole Church, which muſt be a publick intruſtment of the Church beſtowed upon ſome particular perſons for this end in the Church, which is the common ground of authority that is ſet up over a free people as the Church in this caſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Maſter <hi>Bilſons</hi> Title of his Book, is the <hi>Perpetuall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſts Church,</hi> which ſhewes that the Government in the beginning inſtituted by the Apoſtles in the Church, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Governours, are to bee perpetuall, of which this 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.1. was one.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Theſe were ſet up only to prevent ſcandals among the Heathen, under the Chriſtian Magiſtrate; it needs not to be.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Chriſt never intended the being of a Nationall Church in the World.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If once Churches come to bee collected, there is the ſame reaſon for them now, that ever there was in the World.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It was inſtituted to prevent ſcandals, as well within the Church from offending one another, as without from the offending the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> This were to ecclipſe Magiſtracy.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He ruleth for the Magiſtrate, and under him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. and is to bee accomptable to the Magiſtrate for his acts if required.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He ruleth not as the Magiſtrate by the ſword to compell or
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40358:31"/> force, or lay any pecuniary mulcts on thoſe that diſobey, or corporall puniſhment; that indeed were to take the ſword out of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates hand; but by the word and by love, ſhewing what is the command of Chriſt in their ſeverall caſes one to perform to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To me it ſeemes the Apoſtle alludes to this power in the Church only, he writing to the Church, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Let every ſoule be ſubject to the higher Power,</hi> and ſo cals the Church Elder the inferiour power, ſo that this eſtabliſhes the Magiſtrate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> You ſay the Church ſhould ſet him up, and ſo he ſtands not by the Magiſtrate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſponſ.</hi> Indeed, he ſtands <hi>jure divino;</hi> now the priviledge God hath given the Saints, is no more then the Magiſtrate gives to every petty Incorporation, which is, that they ſhall chooſe their own Magiſtrate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> The City Magiſtrate rules by the Law of the publick Magiſtrate</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſponſ.</hi> True, the Elder rules in the Church by the goſpel, which if the world could beare, it were far better if all were ruled by it onely.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Illuſt.</hi> God ruled by the Magiſtracy of <hi>Rome,</hi> by the Law of nature, by <hi>Moſes</hi> government, in a way that made men more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and mercifull one to another then others were: why ſo? God rules one way in the world, another way in the Church, more evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelically, mercifully; the members have a ſpirit of love by which they are taught to ſeek not their own, but the good of one another.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As in proceeding in the Church, firſt tell one or two, then the Church: ſo remedy ſhould be ſought by this way of the Church firſt before any other.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In caſe the member ſubmit not to wholeſome counſell accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the nature of the fact, the eccleſiaſticall Officers being firſt acquainted with it, they may ſuſpend from Sacraments, excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate, and deny ſociety to them untill ſatisfaction in ſome way be given to the Church.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This is authority enough for Chriſt to rule by, which cannot be any way offenſive to Magiſtrates, it is a ſmall boon to be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chriſt: every free ſubject is granted as much in his houſe, and ſhall not Chriſt have it in his Church? what hath Chriſt among the people, where he hath not this?</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:40358:32"/>4. As the Church is divided from the world, ſo is its government, they themſelves though being ſubject to the Magiſtrate as Gods Vicegerent.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Magiſtrate, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.3. is ſaid to be ordained for the praiſe of them that do well; now the Elder in the Church prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſcandals in the world, compoſing differences, preſerving peace in the Church in a Goſpel way, according to Chriſt, doth well; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Magiſtrate is to encourage him, uphold him againſt thoſe that oppoſe him.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Elders of the Church Nationall, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19. are redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the government of the Church particular, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.13. theſe Elders have not to do to judge any without the Church, their authority is bounded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> This is the way to exempt the Church from the publick Magiſtrates command.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are commanded obedience to them, as to the higher Power, and as ordained of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Are to pay Cuſtome and Tribute to them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To defend, honour, and maintaine them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To pray for them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Magiſtracy is exalted by it, in that they rule over thoſe which rule in a more excellenr way then other Under-rulers in the Common-wealth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Churches obedience is better then theirs of the world; they obey of conſcience, the other of neceſſity and feare.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In the world a naturall man may be a fit helper in the Church, he muſt be a wiſe beleever and a Saint.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Magiſtrates office is to ſee the Church under his Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction hath all that liberty, authority and power left free to it, to exerciſe within it ſelfe, Chriſt left it without impaire.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It is neceſſary the Magiſtrate have a help in Church as well as in the world, hee being no more able to do all the one then all the other of himſelfe.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>That the Church ought to chooſe this Officetr.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. They have the choyce of all other as Miniſters and Deacons, and of this alſo; therefore it were wrong to deprive the Church of the choyce of theſe as of the other.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:40358:32"/>2 The Elders Conſtitution depends on his Election by the Church.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 By this the people more gladly aſſent to his determination, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe choſen of themſelves.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. To prevent all meanes of riſe of offence in the Church.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. To ſhew hee muſt be approvedly known for integrity and ability, that is to be intruſted herewith.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. They being enlightned men, know how and whom to chooſe better then others, and therefore God truſted them with theſe priviledges themſelves, and left it not to Miniſters within, or Magiſtrates of or without the Church.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Appl.</hi> Gods people will make no ill uſe of this, that the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate ſhould have cauſe to feare them, for they will chooſe the moſt godly wiſe man among them, which is the beſt choyce for the Magiſtrate and themſelves alſo.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>In the Exerciſe of this Authority.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The Elders of one Church have no Authoritative power over any other Church then their own.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Nor have they to doe with men of the world without the Church.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. I ſuppoſe if differences ariſe between members of ſeverall Churches, then ſome of the Elders of each Church may be nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated to compoſe them.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. If injury be done to a member by one not belonging to any Church, if ſatisfaction cannot be had any other way, he may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale the Offender before the Iudge without ſcandall.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. If injury bee done by a member to one without, the party offended may ſeek reſtitution, and complaine to the Elders againſt him.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. This Goverment is the golden ſcepter; the compulſory power by corporall puniſhments, is as the Iron rod.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. By this, coſt is ſpared, poverty prevented, unity and peace continued, ſcandals prevented to the world without and members within, and edification exceedingly furthered hereby among the Saints.</p>
                  <p>I now adde a word more to prove this generall practice of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:40358:33"/> this government held out in Scriptures to bee exerciſed in the Church.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.1.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Heare O Heavens,</hi> that is the Church or Saints of God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Heare O Earth,</hi> that is the World of unbelievers; two ſorts of perſona being intended herein.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It is emplyed that what he had to ſay concerned both theſe two ſorts of people.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Note in the Metaphor, raine comes down from heaven and not goes up to heaven, as the words here ſignified muſt if heaven be meant literally.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Earths miniſtry is meant in this, <hi>heare the words of my mouth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Church-Miniſtry; 1. It diſtils as the deaw; 2. It drops as the raine on the tender herb; 3. As the ſhowers upon the graſſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. How fitly theſe hold out the differing Miniſtry, the Doctor Miniſtry diſtilling the principles of grace as deaw.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Paſtor dropping.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Evangeliſt ſhowring it down in abundance.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Here are two ſorts expreſſed, <hi>the tender herb, the grown graſſe;</hi> but 3 emplyed, the tender herb being to ſet out the children of the Church and the youth, by diſtilling and dropping, being both ſet before and applyed to the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tender herb.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.9. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>My Dove is one, my perfect one is one, ſhee is deare to her mother, the choice one of her that bare her.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. I choſe this place above other, becauſe Mr <hi>Brightman</hi> and others underſtood it to ſignifie the Goſpel eſtates.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It is without queſtion, wholy ſpoken of the Church.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Here is her birth, as born under the Doctor Miniſtry.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Her Doveſhip or reſervedneſſe to Chriſt under the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Her perfection under the Evangeliſt.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Her unity expreſſed, though under divers Adminiſtrations and eſtates, ſhee is one, ſhe is one.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 13.33. The three meaſures of meale ſignifie the three
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:40358:33"/> ſocieties of Saints; the Leaven and hiding of it, the Goſpel and the threefold Miniſtry thereof.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 13.23. The good ground is ſaid to bring out in ſome a hundred, in other ſixty, in other thirtyfold.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The ſeed is one.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The ground is ſaid to be good.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It is differenced not in it ſelfe, but in its fruit.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. This difference is only threefold, to ſhew amongſt the Saints in the Church, there was a threefold diviſion and no more, the leaſt is thirty, the ſecond doubles it, the third is more then both.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.1. <hi>There was a Reed given me like a rod, and the Angel ſtood and ſaid, Ariſe ond meaſure the Temple of God, and the Altar, and the Worſhipers therein.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. This was done under the ſixth Trump, and reſpects that time in which we live.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In this time, the Goſpel Primitive pattern is revealed, by which at firſt the way and Church of God was ſet up in the world and governed.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. All are reduced to theſe three heads, that are to be meaſured; firſt, the Temple; ſecondly, the Altar; thirdly, the worſhippers.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. A materiall Temple is not meant, God intending not the building of any.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Nor can the myſticall Temple be meant here, that is ſet out in that word worſhippers.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Though not the Temple, yet ſomething of the Temple is alluded unto of God in this place, which I take to bee the forme of the Temple which was divided unto three parts, ſhadowing the three ſocieties of Saints under the Goſpel.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Porch, the Doctor ſociety; 2. The place of Prieſts ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice; 3. The <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> the Evangeliſt ſociety.</p>
                  <p>So that by the meaſuring of the Temple, I ſuppoſe is intended of God, that a ſtrict ſurvey ſhould in theſe times come to be taken of what pertained to each differing Church ſociety, Ordinances and Orders appertaining thereunto.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſecond thing Meaſured is the Altar.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Under the Law, there were two Altars which ſhadowed the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40358:34"/> Divine nature, and humane nature of Chriſt, here reduced to one, mentioned <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Chriſt here repreſented is not to bee meaſured, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. verſ. 34. the Spirit was not given by meaſure to him, ſo that man cannot meaſure Chriſt gifts as Mediator, much leſſe as God; hence this can not be meant of Chriſt, as in himſelfe, but as in the word.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Hence the meaſuring of the Altar, is only that Chriſt ſhould be preached ſo to the ſociety of children as the Word the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure holds him out in the Elementary or Doctrinall part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Paul, Timothy, Sylvanus,</hi> preach only as they are allowed of God therein, the Goſpel, an allowance what to Preach to each ſociety, <hi>viz.</hi> Doctrine in the Doctors, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations in the Paſtor, Conſolation in the Evangeliſts ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That in all the Saints Societies, Chriſt is to be ſet up as an Altar, at which all are to offer, all having to offer to God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as well Infants as men, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.10.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The differing Miniſtries are ſet down in the Temple, in ſeverall diſtinct places.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Doctrine in the Altars meaſuring.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. As theſe are meaſured for the people, ſo the people are mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured for them.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Signifying, none are to be admitted to the firſt Goſpel Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry without meaſuring.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In the Goſpel is a meaſure for all Saints, by which Infants are known to be Infants, young men known from Infants, and Fathers from either; but of theſe more largely in an Expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I intend to ſet forth on the <hi>Revelation,</hi> if God permit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Appli.</hi> That God will in theſe dayes have the Goſpel eſtate re-erected according to the pattern, in which Miniſtry, meanes and members ſhall be all made anſwerable to the Goſpel pattern or meaſure.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. All Formes come ſhort of this, can ſtand no more then <hi>Dagon</hi> before the Arke.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall adde one place more to thoſe in my other Tracts, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to prove mixt ſocieties to ſhew how invalid they are, and how unfitly applied.</p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:40358:34"/>
                  <p>2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.20. <hi>In a great houſe, are veſſels of gold, ſilver, wood and earth;</hi> therefore ſay ſome, in the Church are to be good and bad.</p>
                  <p>Chryſoſt. in locum</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quemadmodum in majori domo neceſſaria est magna differentia vaſorum, ita in toto orbe; non enim eam ſimilttudinem ad Ecceleſiaem refert, ſed ad univerſum mundum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Throp. in Verb.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In magna domo vaſa eſſe diverſa, hunc mundum eſſe non Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am dicit in hoc loco; nam in Eccleſia nil vult ligneum eſſe, ſed ex auro univerſa effecta; aurea qui virtute ſunt praediti; lignea ſunt impii; ſi non ad virtutem, ad mundi tamen confirmationem &amp; sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſunt utiles, vel ad diſpenſationes nonnullas maximè conferunt ut</hi> Pharao.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It will appeare more plaine, if wee conſider God when hee compares the Church, compares it to heaven and heavenly things; this is too earthy to bee a repreſentative of the Church. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.18.21.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10. God ſpeaking of the Church as of a houſe, cals it the houſhold of Faith.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Church is the Patterne of Heavenly not Earthly things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> The Church is compared to a graine of muſtard ſeed, leaven &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſponſ.</hi> Theſe thing a reſpect the grace of the goſpel in men, and the power of God, and not the ſocietyes of Saints, which here is ſaid only to be intended.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>18.</hi> That this forme of Government is aimed at by the Apoſtles, is alſo clearly ſeen in the generall form of the Epiſtle; (which is no ſmall Argument to prove it) as well as part cular inſtructions and inſtances contained in particular places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The Epistle I ſhall inſtance in, is that of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Coloſſians.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe firſt generall part of the Epiſtle, I take to bee generally applyed to the whole Church, and is contained in <hi>chap.</hi> 1. unto
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:40358:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> the firſt foure verſes of the ſecond Chapter.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Part whereof containes Salutations and Prayer for the whole Church, <hi>chap.</hi> 1 from <hi>ver.</hi> 2. to 11.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. From verſe 12. to the end of the 4 verſe <hi>chap.</hi> 2. hee holds out Chriſt, and the Communion <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Timothy</hi> had with them, and they with all Saints in Heaven and Earth in Ieſus Chriſt, as members in a body, of which Chriſt is Head and Saviour.</p>
                  <p>In the next place, the Apoſtle prepares or makes way to deſcend to the particular Church ſocietyes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ver.</hi> 5. He comes to mention the order obſerved by them in the government of their Church.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ver.</hi> 6. He exhorts them as they have received Chriſt, ſo they would walk in him, which implieth there was among them a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent receiving of Chriſt; ſome received him in the goſpel milke, others in the goſpel meate, ſome received him from the Doctor in his Miniſtry, others from the Paſtor in his Miniſtry differing firſt in Degrees, ſecondly in Meanes, thirdly in the Word and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry alſo.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ver.</hi> 7. Hee ſweetly and plainly illuſtrates this truth by a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Metaphor.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Rooting, an alluſion taken from a tree, and fitly to be apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Doctor-Miniſtry, who teacheth the Principles and Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals of Chriſt, the firſt way of receiving Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. And built in him, a Metaphor taken from a houſe not founded, but built up, having a higher degree in it of Chriſt, another way of receiving Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Note the change of the Metaphor hath in it a ſignification of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to bee in the ſocieties the Saints had among them at <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſe,</hi> and alſo of their differing condition in Chriſt; hee otherwiſe might have uſed one Metaphor as ſignificantly, and have ſaid being founded on and builded up in him, &amp;c. but changing the Metaphor, he ſignificantly ſets out and implies a Myſtery therein to bee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. And eſtabliſhed, which is the laſt way of receiving Chriſt, under the diſpenſations of the Goſpel Miniſters in this preſent life.</p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:40358:35"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ap.</hi> That in theſe clearly the order named verſ. 5, is here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, how and in what it did conſiſt, in the Miniſteries right rooting beginners, and building up other believers, and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing others in the grace of the Goſpel by ſeveral degrees, as they had received Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> The Apoſtle, if he meant the change of ſocieties in the change of metaphors in the firſt, Why he did not change them in the laſt?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Resp.</hi> The thing was ſufficiently cleared in the firſt metaphor to thoſe Churches, who had this order erected among them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 This of eſtabliſhed may be applied to other metaphors, as well as that of building or planting.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Though the metaphor be not changed, the act is a different act, which ſhews a different means to be uſed for the end intended by the Apoſtle in the thing ſpoken of.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 The text clearly proves it, that this order generally, for the rooting, building, and eſtabliſhing, is to be done by teaching: ſo ſaith the holy Ghoſt, <hi>As ye have been taught.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 The adverb <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſhews, that in the quality of teaching was contained the manner of receiving Chriſt; and ſhews, that as they differed in the receiving of Chriſt, ſo in the teaching Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>General.</hi> From verſ. 11 of chap. 2. to the end of verſ. 11 of chap. 3. the Apoſtle applieth himſelf onely to ſpeak unto the rooting of rooted Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Shewing there was to be a ſpiritual Circumciſion wrought in them, by which is occaſioned a putting off the body of the ſins of the fleſh, verſ. 11. which conſiſts in a ſpiritual ſenſe given them of ſin and nature, and an abominating of them required of thoſe made members.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 After this they are to be baptized, in which they are ſaid to be dead, and riſen with him through the faith of the operation of God.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 After this, verſ. 13, 14, 15, ye have what Chriſt hath done for thoſe thus baptized, and how he is to be preached unto them.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 From verſ. 16. ye have the end contained, the abolition of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:40358:36"/> ceremonies, things which uſually were a trouble to the weak, or the infant-ſociety of the Saints.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 From chap 3. verſ. 1, to the end of verſ. 8, he provoketh the Saints to a ſpiritual trial of themſelves, their eſtates and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſhews what accompanieth true regeneration in the Saints. <hi>V.</hi> 9. he gives the reaſon, they have put off the old man with his deeds, making a publike renunciation of the deeds of the fleſh before baptiſme, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. and have put on the new, that is, by co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants, promiſes, by ſacraments, in which all are alike intereſſed: for nor Greek nor Jew, circumciſion nor uncircumciſion, Barbarian nor Scythian, bond nor free, but Chriſt is all in all. Application in theſe verſes predicted and applied, ye have generally ſet down what is to be taught the ſociety of infants, and what is required of them, though the firſt Epiſtle of <hi>John</hi> is that which ſolely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the Infants of the Church; the Apoſtles, as they ſaw occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, writing ſometimes more largely of the duty of one Society to one Church then to another, as they ſaw occaſion required in the Churches eſtate they wrote unto.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond part of Miniſtery, or the Society of Young men, as concerned in <hi>verſ.</hi> 12, 13.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Is intimated in a ſecond putting on of Chriſt, which is to be according to the elect of God, as holy and beloved ones.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This is to be manifeſted in the inward ſpirituall operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Chriſt in the minde, ſet out in bowels of mercy, kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, humbleneſſe of minde, meekneſſe, long-ſuffering, ver. 13. <hi>Forbearing one another, forgiving one another; If any man have a quarrell againſt any man, even as</hi> CHRIST <hi>forgave you, ſo doe ye alſo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. In theſe doe I ſuppoſe are contained the things chiefly to be preſſed on the Saints of the Paſtors Society, and to reprove thoſe that fail amongſt them in obedience hereunto.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Not that here, or in any other Epiſtle in particular, is all to be taught in this Society; but the whole Scripture pertaining to that Society, is, that is only ſufficient to inſtruct them to, and fit them for the perfecting Miniſtery.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. 1 <hi>Ep.</hi> of <hi>John</hi> is only for the Rooting of Saints.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:40358:36"/>1 <hi>Ep.</hi> of <hi>Peter,</hi> for the building up of Saints.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ep.</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> for the ſtabliſhing of Saints, which here now as the Third generall Part of Miniſtery; comes to be handled; and is contained in <hi>Verſe</hi> 14, and <hi>Verſe</hi> 17. In which Chriſt is to be put on in Charity, which is ſaid, <hi>To be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, This is ſaid to be the bond of perfection; here, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, hath reſpect to Church bonds, by which men were bound to Chriſt in ſome publique way, and to one another.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>Verſe</hi> 15. they ſhould have the peace of God rule in them.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, The Word of God dwell richly in them, in all wiſdom, teaching and admoniſhing one another in Pſalms, Songs, Hymnes.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It is clear, theſe things were not to be applyed to the Society of Infants, nor were all beleevers capable of it, onely the men in Chriſt are here ſpoken unto, who were to have theſe things in a more abundant and excellent way then others were, and whether theſe Pſalms were the Scripture-Pſalms only, or whether thoſe of that Society only were to be ſpiritually gifted therein; I ſhall not undertake to determine, they were to be emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently gifted doubtleſs in all grace.</p>
                  <p>That that makes this doctrine the more clear; is,</p>
                  <p n="1">1 That with theſe he ends his doctrine to the Church, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no other Society but theſe in or of the Church.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Hence he applyeth himſelf to domeſtick duties in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Verſe</hi> 17, 18. is ſet down what is required of the wife to the husband, and husband to the wife.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Verſe</hi> 20, &amp; 21. what is required of Parents to children, and Children to parents.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. From <hi>ver.</hi> 22, to <hi>ver.</hi> 25. Servants duties to their Maſters.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. <hi>ver.</hi> 1. the duty of Maſters to their Servants.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Ver.</hi> 2, &amp; 3. Family duties to God are ſet down to be exerciſed in private; which are; 1 <hi>Prayer.</hi> 2 <hi>Watchfulneſs.</hi> 3 <hi>Thankſgiving.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>Ver.</hi> 4. Eſpecially they are to pray for, 1 The Goſpel. 2 The Miniſters thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:40358:37"/>
                  <head>Now from publike Duties in Church, and private in the family, he cometh to ſhew what is to be done towards thoſe that are without the Church, <hi>Ver. 5. &amp; 6.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. In reſpect of their behavior, it muſt be in wiſdom.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In their Speech, it muſt be ſeaſoned with Salt.</p>
                  <p>And thus having ſhewed them, how things ought to be with them in the Goſpel-way, he comes to ſhew them how things were with him; knowing they would be deſirous of his welbeing, that ſhewed ſuch a deſire to them in him of theirs.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. And thus he leaves in general, to the report of <hi>Tychicus</hi> and <hi>Oneſimus,</hi> Verſ. 7, 8, 9.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Verſ. 11. He tells who miniſter with him at <hi>Rome,</hi> Verſ. 12, 13. Commends <hi>Epaphras,</hi> Verſ. 14. Remembers the ſalutes of <hi>Demas</hi> and <hi>Luke.</hi> Verſ. 15. Salutes the <hi>Laodiceans.</hi> Verſ. 16. Commands the Reading of the Epiſtle. Verſ. 17. Mindes <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chippus</hi> of his miniſtry. And Verſ. 18. Concludes the Epiſtle.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>19. For the ſetting of the Goſpel ſtate up, it muſt be ſet up as in the beginning.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. There muſt be a Mother-Church, in which the true form is to be ſet up.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Then there muſt be Elders ordained, and ſent forth to thoſe Cities firſt that will receive the Goſpel, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.23. <hi>Luke</hi> 8.6. Chriſt preached in the villages, preparing for the Goſpel-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 47.8. as under the Temple ſtate the warers were propheſied to be.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. And then a way and means is offered to thoſe other Towns, that are capable of this Government, to ſet it up in them alſo.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Before this can be ſet up, Parochial bounds ought to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Where are not publike meeting places, there any convenient private houſes are to be made uſe of.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. That thoſe Miniſters that are not of the Church miniſtry, be not admitted to baptize, or adminiſter the Sacraments of the Lords Supper in the place they exerciſe.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. That they are to be ſubject to the Presbytery of that Church,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:40358:37"/> they are Members of, that ſo they preach no other Doctrine, but what is to be taught without the Church.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. That the Miniſters, without the Church, be Members of ſome Church near them, or not be admitted to miniſter, to which they ſhall miniſter, preparing men for it. It is obſervable, there was no ſtanding miniſtry in the Apoſtles time, but where were Churches of Saints in Communion; the other miniſtry, if they were perſecuted in a place, may leave it.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Thoſe that teach without the Church, ſhould be maintained by the ſtate allowance, Tithes diſſolved, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. Let him that is catechized, communicate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which without the Magiſtrates help, would not be done by unbeleevers, who love their Gold not their God.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. The Church Teachers ſhould freely be maintained by their Members, as by a freewil-offering.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. The whole of the Papal, Epiſcopal, Presbyterial Form, is to be diſſolved.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. This was done in the Moſaical Government, and ſhall it not be in the Antichriſtian?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Chriſt ſaith, no man patcheth a new garment with an old peece, no not a peece.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It ſeems to me plain, That the ſingle Antichriſtian Miniſter, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.18. had nothing Gold but the Talent he hid, which was the Word in a ſtrange tongue; or if any thing elſe, it was and will be taken from him.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. It is well obſerved by One, <hi>Deum ſolere uno ſigillo varias materias ſignare.</hi> The truth wherof we may ſee in the two Temples before Chriſt; the firſt was burnt and deſtroyed by the <hi>Chaldees;</hi> ſo the firſt Temple eſtate by perſecution, was deſtroyed by An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, and the Heathen Emperors; the ſecond, is builded by <hi>Zorubabel,</hi> which is by Interpretation <hi>Fan Bable;</hi> which is as truly to be verified now, as then, and more fully in us, then them; for they did not indeed Fan <hi>Bable,</hi> but thoſe ſet up the ſecond Temple under the Goſpel, ſhall do it.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.5. <hi>Behold, I will make all things new.</hi> All things, not ſome, in the buſineſs of the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> are to be made new. The maner how it ſhall be done, is ſet down by <hi>Peter,</hi> and men cannot prevent it, but thoſe are happy that fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:40358:38"/> it, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10. The Heavens and the hoſt of them, they paſs away, and are diſſolved, and burnt up. I ſhall, God willing, in my Expoſition of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> ſpeak of the new Earth. Verſ. 11. Then there is the new Heaven follows, in which dwelleth in Righteouſneſs; ſo that it is a moſt certain truth, all preſent Forms, Government, and ways of worſhip muſt be, yea, ſhall be diſſolved before, yea, and for the advancement of the true way of Goſpel worſhip. <hi>Revel.</hi> 6.12, 13, 14. ſhews you the time when this ſhall be, and that is under the opening of the ſixt Seal, in which, we at this inſtant are under, and ſee the effects pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, according to the truth of the great God revealed; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the mockers and ſcoffers of the world, have derided it; ſo that they muſt and ſhall have their mouths ſtopped, and be made aſhamed at it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> In many great Towns and places, where have been a faithful, painful Miniſtry, and are a godly people to conſtitute a Church in, they have but one publike meeting place; and how then can the ſeveral Miniſtries be ſet up there in.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> The Synagogues were the places the Apoſtles preached in, to men without, and ſeparated the Diſciples to private houſes. In which, for the pureſt times of the Church, the Saints were miniſtred unto, and had no publike meeting places as now. Which order is ſo clearly ſet out unto us in Scripture, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be excepted againſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 28.30.</p>
                  <p>The neceſſity hereof appears.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. From the confuſion in the Church, and Church-Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances; in which, as they are now exerciſed, nothing is done to the Saints edification.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Men without the Spirit, and without underſtanding, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pray, nor praiſe God; but minde the things ſung or ſaid, in a carnal maner againſt the minde of God, they are dead to God, to whom God is not a God, nor they a people.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In Preaching to Saints, the Doctrine to be preached to the world, cannot be to edification.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. And as there is a neceſſity of dividing the World from Saints, ſo Saints from Saints; without which can be no right edification among the Saints.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Illuſt.</hi> The Goſpel is compared to Leaven; by degrees the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:40358:38"/> lump; ſo the Goſpel is to be preached to men without, to lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them, or gather them to the Society of Saints, which would be gathered as yet into a few Churches. Now as the Saints are increaſed, and fit matter of a church prepared, the Miniſter of the place may require helpers to be joyned with him for the conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the church to be conſtituted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> The people will not endure it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp.</hi> The people ordained to eternal life will rejoyce in it: others that do not, are not worthy of it.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>Hebr.</hi> chapt. 8.20. we have mention made of two covenants, the new and the old; under which two covenants there are to be differing adminiſtrations; the one of which ceaſeth in the being of the other. But before we proceed, we may (for the better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of things) conſider the covenant as it was made with <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 17.2. and 7. which is made to one man, a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever in Chriſt. <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.16. to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed were the promiſes: he ſaith not, <hi>And to ſeeds, as of many; but as of one, and to thy ſeed, which is Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now the adminiſtrations of divine Worſhip were exerciſed by the firſt-born of the Family: they were the Prieſts during its time of ſtanding.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtle in this chapter ſpeaks of the ſtate of the covenant as after it was made to <hi>Moſes, ver.</hi> 9. when God took them by the hand to lead them out of <hi>Egypt.</hi> Now in this there was (in reſpect of the adminiſtrations and extent of it) ſuch a difference, as if it had been another covenant.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 It is made to the whole Nation, <hi>Exod:</hi> 6.6, 7. Say to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael, &amp;c. <hi>I will take you to me for a people, and I will be to you a God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 The Prieſthood is now a National Prieſthood, <hi>ver.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 The ſacrifices are for all the people, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.37.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 The Tabernacle is the ſtanding place for publick worſhip to the whole people, mentioned <hi>ver.</hi> 5. Which cleerly proves, that God reſpected the adminiſtrations under the covenant, as made to the Iſraelites nationally in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and not as made with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> before; under which the people lived untill <hi>John</hi> the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt.</p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:40358:39"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ver.</hi> 9. He ſheweth that the covenant made with man under the Goſpel ſhould be far differing from that made with the Iſraelites in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and therefore called a new covenant, to which the old ſhould give place, decay, and vaniſh away.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The miniſtry under the new covenant (or rather, new ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations of the covenant) is ſaid to be a more excellent mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, Chriſt himſelf being the high Prieſt and Mediatour, and not <hi>Moſes,</hi> intimated <hi>ver.</hi> 2. nor <hi>Aaron.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Having better promiſes, <hi>Exod.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 6. it was to bring them from the burdens of the Egyptians, and redeem them, and bring them into the Land of <hi>Canaan:</hi> This to be heirs of the Kingdom of heaven, and redeemed from hell.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. A better covenant, in that under it they have the Laws of God written in their hearts and mindes: under <hi>Moſes,</hi> in ſtony Tables.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Shewing, That God would under theſe adminiſtrations have none to be his people in communion, but ſuch as had his Law, that is, of Faith, written in their hearts: <hi>The Law was given by Moſes; but grace and truth came by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And ſo ſheweth, that the Goſpel covenant, or the adminiſtrations of the covenant under the Goſpel, admitted not of a Nationall Society; and in this the new covenant is ſaid to excell the old; this being the ground of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and being to go before it.</p>
                  <p>This is illuſtrated, in that when Chriſt ſet up the Goſpel Church, he called men out of the National Church, requiring that men firſt ſhould be taught and beleeve, before they be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the church: in which was plainly the vaniſhing of the old, and the adminiſtrations of the new ſet out. So that to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Nationall church, is to aboliſh the new, and ſet up the old covenant, and is Judaiſing, being quite contrary to the tenour of the Goſpel adminiſtrations.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ver.</hi> 10. The holy Ghoſt ſets down the time when the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations of the new covenant take place, that is, after thoſe dayes: <hi>viz.</hi> after that <hi>Moſes</hi> Miniſtry ſhould have an end, then the new covenant ſhould take place and begin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ver.</hi> 11. It is ſaid, They ſhall not teach every man his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and his brother, ſaying, <hi>Know the Lord</hi> (as under the old covenant,) <hi>for all ſhall know mee from the greatest to the least.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:40358:39"/>
                  <p>The Epoſition ſome make of theſe words to elude the true ſenſe of them, is, That in the laſt days there ſhall be ſuch abundance of knowledg, that all ſhall know God; but if we apply the words be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or after this, its eaſily refuted, as that all ſhall have it written in their hearts, or that God will be merciful to the unrighteouſneſs of all, and not remember their ſins any more, is a thing I think that none will dare affirm, when all that have this knowledg here ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of written in their hearts ſhall have.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Note, that theſe words were to be fulfilled after the date of the old Covenant, under the Adminiſtrations of the New, in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles times or in all times to come, in which the true Goſpel-Diſpenſations under the New Covenant ſhall be adminiſtred, and have no reſpect more to time to come, more then the Apoſtles times paſt.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The words, <hi>all ſhall know me,</hi> are not to be underſtond only as a propheſie of the abundance of knowledg to be revealed of God under the Diſpenſation of Grace: but alſo are to be underſtood as a conditional thing that was required of all, even the leaſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, the Infant in Chriſt, before he could enjoy Communion of the Goſpel. Adminiſtrations with the Saints; this is clearly held out, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. <hi>l</hi> 3. I write to you fathers (who are here ſaid to be the greateſt,) becauſe ye have known him which is from the beginning; and then after, I write to you little children, becauſe ye have known the Father, (and theſe are here called the leaſt,) who without this knowledg are uncapable of being writ unto, or preached unto in the Goſpel way, how much more unfit are they then for other more ſpiritual exerciſes.</p>
                  <p>And hence the Apoſtle ſhews, That the New Covenant requires the leaſt Chriſtian to have the knowledg of God in him, or he is not to be admitted a Church Member, or accounted a Covenanter with God.</p>
                  <p>This knowledg and Communion with God ſhall have forgive-of ſins and iniquities with it, which make the knowledg of God ſweet in its ſoul to it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quere,</hi> Are none to be admitted Members under the New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:40358:40"/> but thoſe have the Law written in their hearts, and have their iniquities pardoned?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſp,</hi> All that are true Members have, and all that are admitted ſhould have.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The condition of making Members muſt be ſomething viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the Church being not able to judg of the inviſible eſtate of men.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Here the condition is contained in the 11. Verſe, which is, That the leaſt Member ſhall have a knowledg of God, and be able to manifeſt it to the Church, whether it be in his heart or not, <hi>God</hi> only knoweth.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. To make him a Covenanter, he is to profeſs his faith in <hi>God,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the knowledg he hath of <hi>God,</hi> in which he is ſaid to take <hi>God</hi> to him to be his <hi>God,</hi> and ſo became a viſible Member of the Church.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. This Covenant was made with the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> drawn from I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. And after the great defection made under An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, it comes to be made again at the beginning of the eſtate of the new <hi>Ieruſalem, Rev.</hi> 21.3. which time is yet to be.</p>
                  <p>I deſire that it may be ſeriouſly conſidered, how this making National Churches doth wholy deſtroy, not only Chriſtian privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, but how it alſo makes void much of the Scriptures, which are by this means as good as razed out of the Book of God.</p>
                  <p>As in the Scriptures that ſpeak of the world, as oppoſed to the Church.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. I deſire thoſe that maintain National Churches, to ſhew where the world is in this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> that they account wholly to be of the Church or a Church. <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.29. <hi>I have choſen you out of the world, therefore the world hateth you. Iohn</hi> 17.9, <hi>I pray not for the world: Verſ.</hi> 6. <hi>I pray for them thou haſt given me out of the world.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.32. <hi>That ye ſhould not be condemned with the world,</hi> and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, <hi>be ye not conformed to this preſent evil world.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. I deſire to know how theſe Scriptures can be made right uſe of, or be rightly applyed to the uſe of Saints, until theſe are divided one from the other.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. How this doth hinder the Manifeſtation of the Calling of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:40358:40"/> Saints, and the Manifeſtation of their love to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Graces.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Now it hardens wicked men, while there is no difference made between Saints and them in Church Privildges, and how it ſuddens the hearts of Saints.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. How the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in the Saints is obſcured by theſe means, whom <hi>God</hi> hath endowed, as it were, with glorious light to ſhine to the world by.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. How the government of the Church can otherwiſe be then confuſed, whiles carnal men are admitted, who by no means can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bear the yoke, or tread the path of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. How this deſtruction, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.32. gave no offence, nor to Jew, nor to Gentile, nor to the Church: here the Jew and Gentile are ſet down in oppoſition to the Church, which the Saints muſt not offend, according to the Apoſtles mind, can be obſerved among us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Application</hi> to Miniſters, to take heed of conſenting to theſe things; this was the great abomination Antichriſt was to do in the world, even to make deſolate the Church, pull down her wals, pull up her marks, and deſtroy her bounds.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In this grand defection Antichriſt hath no leſs part in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> then in <hi>Rome;</hi> and Popery is never deſtroyed while this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, nor Reformation made</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Nor will <hi>God</hi> make any peace with the people of this Land, until this be reformed, and the Church liberties and priviledges be reſtored, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 2.22.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Appl.</hi> 2. I ſhall end all in the exhortations of <hi>Haggai</hi> to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, as being that properly pertains now to you, as then to them to whom God immediately ſent it.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The houſe lyeth waſte.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. God ends the Propheſies with the Gentiles, <hi>Haggai</hi> 2.22, 23 in which God would let you know this book concerned the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:40358:41"/> and that the Scripture is never fulfilled, until done among them; That that Scripture ſpeaks will be found true, and no lye, in theſe days, amongſt us, which ſome ſay is only proper to us of <hi>Europe:</hi> O ye of the Magiſtracy, ariſe, begin to build the Lords houſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. To the Miniſters, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.27. <hi>for the over ſpreading of abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations he ſhall make it deſolate.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. This deſolation is ſaid to be to the end of the war, that is, that war that Antichriſt ſhall make with the Saints, <hi>v.</hi> 26. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.7</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This deſolation is to be until the confirmation, and that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, be poured on the deſolate.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 1. If the Church be not in her deſolate eſtate?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Where or when that time is out?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If our War be not part of that wrath ſaid to be determined to be poured out.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Where while the Church is left to its deſolation, it be not a certain token all is not poured out; and the farther that time is off, the more wrath is to come?</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Where thoſe hinder the reſtoration of the Temple-eſtate, are not the only cauſes of our lying under this heavy eſtate?</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Where if the Church be once reſtored, God would not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately give us peace and mercy? try the Lord in this thing, and you will be bleſſed that truſt him.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Do not fear the Lords providing means, comforts, and mercy neceſſary, the Lord will not be wanting to us in his own way, and break us better in Gods way, then all earthly good in any other: that which generally we have had other way have come to little.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Appl.</hi> 3. To the People: Do not you ſhew your ſelves back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in <hi>Haggai</hi> 1.2? This people ſay, the time is not come to build the Lords houſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. God hath curſed you as the Jews, <hi>v.</hi> 6, 9.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If you ſhew your ſelves willing, God will then bleſs you as them, <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.28. Take my yoke upon you, my yoke is eaſie.</p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:40358:41"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Appl</hi> 4. To the Souldiers. 1. Be faithful in your undertakings, be humble under your victories, be thankful for your deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; labor to do all you do for the glory of God, and the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Goſpel, that the Lords cauſe ſuffer not reproach, and the Lord may give you leave to ſee the glorious goodneſs will at laſt ariſe to this poor harrowed Nation from your hard labor, and be made partakers of the Lords grace your ſelves, and do it not for others only, that only is able to ſati fie you for your loſs of Blood, your lack of Means, and reſtleſs pains. O look on this as your arrears, and you ſhall finde in <hi>God</hi> a better pay-maſter then any you have yet met withal, and from whom you have much more to receive then from the Eſtate, and with whom your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is more acceptable then with man, as hath been abundantly witneſſed; keep cloſe to him, you have had, and may again have much need of him, &amp; can do nothing without him: let not the world nor conſcience be able juſtly to ſay, ye do any thing againſt <hi>God,</hi> and be ſure that in what ye do for <hi>God,</hi> ye ſhall not want help to do it, and at laſt <hi>God</hi> will make your enemies love you, and the Saints of <hi>God</hi> will pray for you, and love you in the Lord always</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Appl.</hi> To the City, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.19. <hi>The City of the Nations fell.</hi> This is the falling time; if ye fall from Antichriſt to Chriſt, it is a happy fall, if not, a woful one is predicted, in you is found all the blood of the Engliſh Martyrs, the injuſtice and pride of the land.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Appl.</hi> To men of differing Judgments:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Ye that are for Epiſcopacy, in this is the Angel Miniſtry ye contend for, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.1. caſt out of the Church as extraordinary, brought in again.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Ye for Presbytery, in this ye have the true Church Presbyters, they governing joyntly the Church.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Ye for Independency, here is a Church governed by its own Officers, within it ſelf, without any others to rule in it.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Ye Antinomianiſts; here is the goſpel purely preached to the Saints, the Law to unbeleevers.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Ye Seekers, here is a Church-government a long time hid, now to be revealed according to your expectation.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:40358:42"/>6, Ye Anabaptiſts, as the Aſſembly ſay, the conſtituting of the Church was and is to be of Beleevers, which are after to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, as confeſſed to be done in the Apoſtles day.</p>
                  <p>So that without all queſtion, when the true way of <hi>God</hi> ſhall be revealed, the ſpirits of all that are led of <hi>God,</hi> ſhall be gathered ſweetly, unanimouſly, and gladly into communion one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther again, though now divided, that <hi>Ephraim</hi> ſhall not envy <hi>Juda,</hi> nor <hi>Juda, Ephraim</hi> more; which is that which is only ſought for by me, and to be ſought for of all that love the Lord and his Saints in truth, and expect mercy from him at his appearing.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:40358:42"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
